IX

Mr. and Mrs. Boffin in Consultation

Betaking himself straight homeward, Mr. Boffin, without further let or hindrance, arrived at the Bower, and gave Mrs. Boffin (in a walking dress of black velvet and feathers, like a mourning coach-horse) an account of all he had said and done since breakfast.

“This brings us round, my dear,” he then pursued, “to the question we left unfinished: namely, whether there’s to be any new go-in for Fashion.”

“Now, I’ll tell you what I want, Noddy,” said Mrs. Boffin, smoothing her dress with an air of immense enjoyment, “I want Society.”

“Fashionable Society, my dear?”

“Yes!” cried Mrs. Boffin, laughing with the glee of a child. “Yes! It’s no good my being kept here like waxwork; is it now?”

“People have to pay to see waxwork, my dear,” returned her husband, “whereas (though you’d be cheap at the same money) the neighbours is welcome to see you for nothing.”

“But it don’t answer,” said the cheerful Mrs. Boffin. “When we worked like the neighbours, we suited one another. Now we have left work off; we have left off suiting one another.”

“What, do you think of beginning work again?” Mr. Boffin hinted.

“Out of the question! We have come into a great fortune, and we must do what’s right by our fortune; we must act up to it.”

Mr. Boffin, who had a deep respect for his wife’s intuitive wisdom, replied, though rather pensively: “I suppose we must.”

“It’s never been acted up to yet, and, consequently, no good has come of it,” said Mrs. Boffin.

“True, to the present time,” Mr. Boffin assented, with his former pensiveness, as he took his seat upon his settle. “I hope good may be coming of it in the future time. Towards which, what’s your views, old lady?”

Mrs. Boffin, a smiling creature, broad of figure and simple of nature, with her hands folded in her lap, and with buxom creases in her throat, proceeded to expound her views.

“I say, a good house in a good neighbourhood, good things about us, good living, and good society. I say, live like our means, without extravagance, and be happy.”

“Yes. I say be happy, too,” assented the still pensive Mr. Boffin. “Lor-a-mussy!” exclaimed Mrs. Boffin, laughing and clapping her hands, and gaily rocking herself to and fro, “when I think of me in a light yellow chariot and pair, with silver boxes to the wheels—”

“Oh! you was thinking of that, was you, my dear?”

“Yes!” cried the delighted creature. “And with a footman up behind, with a bar across, to keep his legs from being poled! And with a coachman up in front, sinking down into a seat big enough for three of him, all covered with upholstery in green and white! And with two bay horses tossing their heads and stepping higher than they trot longways! And with you and me leaning back inside, as grand as ninepence! Oh-h-h-h My! Ha ha ha ha ha!”

Mrs. Boffin clapped her hands again, rocked herself again, beat her feet upon the floor, and wiped the tears of laughter from her eyes.

“And what, my old lady,” inquired Mr. Boffin, when he also had sympathetically laughed: “what’s your views on the subject of the Bower?”

“Shut it up. Don’t part with it, but put somebody in it, to keep it.”

“Any other views?”

“Noddy,” said Mrs. Boffin, coming from her fashionable sofa to his side on the plain settle, and hooking her comfortable arm through his, “Next I think—and I really have been thinking early and late—of the disappointed girl; her that was so cruelly disappointed, you know, both of her husband and his riches. Don’t you think we might do something for her? Have her to live with us? Or something of that sort?”

“Ne‑ver once thought of the way of doing it!” cried Mr. Boffin, smiting the table in his admiration. “What a thinking steam-ingein this old lady is. And she don’t know how she does it. Neither does the ingein!”

Mrs. Boffin pulled his nearest ear, in acknowledgment of this piece of philosophy, and then said, gradually toning down to a motherly strain: “Last, and not least, I have taken a fancy. You remember dear little John Harmon, before he went to school? Over yonder across the yard, at our fire? Now that he is past all benefit of the money, and it’s come to us, I should like to find some orphan child, and take the boy and adopt him and give him John’s name, and provide for him. Somehow, it would make me easier, I fancy. Say it’s only a whim—”

“But I don’t say so,” interposed her husband.

“No, but deary, if you did—”

“I should be a beast if I did,” her husband interposed again.

“That’s as much as to say you agree? Good and kind of you, and like you, deary! And don’t you begin to find it pleasant now,” said Mrs. Boffin, once more radiant in her comely way from head to foot, and once more smoothing her dress with immense enjoyment, “don’t you begin to find it pleasant already, to think that a child will be made brighter, and better, and happier, because of that poor sad child that day? And isn’t it pleasant to know that the good will be done with the poor sad child’s own money?”

“Yes; and it’s pleasant to know that you are Mrs. Boffin,” said her husband, “and it’s been a pleasant thing to know this many and many a year!” It was ruin to Mrs. Boffin’s aspirations, but, having so spoken, they sat side by side, a hopelessly unfashionable pair.

These two ignorant and unpolished people had guided themselves so far on in their journey of life, by a religious sense of duty and desire to do right. Ten thousand weaknesses and absurdities might have been detected in the breasts of both; ten thousand vanities additional, possibly, in the breast of the woman. But the hard wrathful and sordid nature that had wrung as much work out of them as could be got in their best days, for as little money as could be paid to hurry on their worst, had never been so warped but that it knew their moral straightness and respected it. In its own despite, in a constant conflict with itself and them, it had done so. And this is the eternal law. For, Evil often stops short at itself and dies with the doer of it; but Good, never.

Through his most inveterate purposes, the dead Jailer of Harmony Jail had known these two faithful servants to be honest and true. While he raged at them and reviled them for opposing him with the speech of the honest and true, it had scratched his stony heart, and he had perceived the powerlessness of all his wealth to buy them if he had addressed himself to the attempt. So, even while he was their griping taskmaster and never gave them a good word, he had written their names down in his will. So, even while it was his daily declaration that he mistrusted all mankind—and sorely indeed he did mistrust all who bore any resemblance to himself—he was as certain that these two people, surviving him, would be trustworthy in all things from the greatest to the least, as he was that he must surely die.

Mr. and Mrs. Boffin, sitting side by side, with Fashion withdrawn to an immeasurable distance, fell to discussing how they could best find their orphan. Mrs. Boffin suggested advertisement in the newspapers, requesting orphans answering annexed description to apply at the Bower on a certain day; but Mr. Boffin wisely apprehending obstruction of the neighbouring thoroughfares by orphan swarms, this course was negatived. Mrs. Boffin next suggested application to their clergyman for a likely orphan. Mr. Boffin thinking better of this scheme, they resolved to call upon the reverend gentleman at once, and to take the same opportunity of making acquaintance with Miss Bella Wilfer. In order that these visits might be visits of state, Mrs. Boffin’s equipage was ordered out.

This consisted of a long hammer-headed old horse, formerly used in the business, attached to a four-wheeled chaise of the same period, which had long been exclusively used by the Harmony Jail poultry as the favourite laying-place of several discreet hens. An unwonted application of corn to the horse, and of paint and varnish to the carriage, when both fell in as a part of the Boffin legacy, had made what Mr. Boffin considered a neat turnout of the whole; and a driver being added, in the person of a long hammer-headed young man who was a very good match for the horse, left nothing to be desired. He, too, had been formerly used in the business, but was now entombed by an honest jobbing tailor of the district in a perfect Sepulchre of coat and gaiters, sealed with ponderous buttons.

Behind this domestic, Mr. and Mrs. Boffin took their seats in the back compartment of the vehicle: which was sufficiently commodious, but had an undignified and alarming tendency, in getting over a rough crossing, to hiccup itself away from the front compartment. On their being descried emerging from the gates of the Bower, the neighbourhood turned out at door and window to salute the Boffins. Among those who were ever and again left behind, staring after the equipage, were many youthful spirits, who hailed it in stentorian tones with such congratulations as “Nod‑dy Boffin!” “Boffin’s money!” “Down with the dust, Boffin!” and other similar compliments. These, the hammer-headed young man took in such ill part that he often impaired the majesty of the progress by pulling up short, and making as though he would alight to exterminate the offenders; a purpose from which he only allowed himself to be dissuaded after long and lively arguments with his employers.

At length the Bower district was left behind, and the peaceful dwelling of the Reverend Frank Milvey was gained. The Reverend Frank Milvey’s abode was a very modest abode, because his income was a very modest income. He was officially accessible to every blundering old woman who had incoherence to bestow upon him, and readily received the Boffins. He was quite a young man, expensively educated and wretchedly paid, with quite a young wife and half a dozen quite young children. He was under the necessity of teaching and translating from the classics, to eke out his scanty means, yet was generally expected to have more time to spare than the idlest person in the parish, and more money than the richest. He accepted the needless inequalities and inconsistencies of his life, with a kind of conventional submission that was almost slavish; and any daring layman who would have adjusted such burdens as his, more decently and graciously, would have had small help from him.

With a ready patient face and manner, and yet with a latent smile that showed a quick enough observation of Mrs. Boffin’s dress, Mr. Milvey, in his little book-room—charged with sounds and cries as though the six children above were coming down through the ceiling, and the roasting leg of mutton below were coming up through the floor—listened to Mrs. Boffin’s statement of her want of an orphan.

“I think,” said Mr. Milvey, “that you have never had a child of your own, Mr. and Mrs. Boffin?”

Never.

“But, like the Kings and Queens in the fairy tales, I suppose you have wished for one?”

In a general way, yes.

Mr. Milvey smiled again, as he remarked to himself “Those kings and queens were always wishing for children.” It occurring to him, perhaps, that if they had been curates, their wishes might have tended in the opposite direction.

“I think,” he pursued, “we had better take Mrs. Milvey into our council. She is indispensable to me. If you please, I’ll call her.”

So, Mr. Milvey called, “Margaretta, my dear!” and Mrs. Milvey came down. A pretty, bright little woman, something worn by anxiety, who had repressed many pretty tastes and bright fancies, and substituted in their stead, schools, soup, flannel, coals, and all the weekday cares and Sunday coughs of a large population, young and old. As gallantly had Mr. Milvey repressed much in himself that naturally belonged to his old studies and old fellow-students, and taken up among the poor and their children with the hard crumbs of life.

“Mr. and Mrs. Boffin, my dear, whose good fortune you have heard of.”

Mrs. Milvey, with the most unaffected grace in the world, congratulated them, and was glad to see them. Yet her engaging face, being an open as well as a perceptive one, was not without her husband’s latent smile.

“Mrs. Boffin wishes to adopt a little boy, my dear.”

Mrs. Milvey, looking rather alarmed, her husband added:

“An orphan, my dear.”

“Oh!” said Mrs. Milvey, reassured for her own little boys.

“And I was thinking, Margaretta, that perhaps old Mrs. Goody’s grandchild might answer the purpose.”

“Oh my dear Frank! I don’t think that would do!”

“No?”

“Oh no!”

The smiling Mrs. Boffin, feeling it incumbent on her to take part in the conversation, and being charmed with the emphatic little wife and her ready interest, here offered her acknowledgments and inquired what there was against him?

“I don’t think,” said Mrs. Milvey, glancing at the Reverend Frank, “—and I believe my husband will agree with me when he considers it again—that you could possibly keep that orphan clean from snuff. Because his grandmother takes so many ounces, and drops it over him.”

“But he would not be living with his grandmother then, Margaretta,” said Mr. Milvey.

“No, Frank, but it would be impossible to keep her from Mrs. Boffin’s house; and the more there was to eat and drink there, the oftener she would go. And she is an inconvenient woman. I hope it’s not uncharitable to remember that last Christmas Eve she drank eleven cups of tea, and grumbled all the time. And she is not a grateful woman, Frank. You recollect her addressing a crowd outside this house, about her wrongs, when, one night after we had gone to bed, she brought back the petticoat of new flannel that had been given her, because it was too short.”

“That’s true,” said Mr. Milvey. “I don’t think that would do. Would little Harrison—”

“Oh, Frank!” remonstrated his emphatic wife.

“He has no grandmother, my dear.”

“No, but I don’t think Mrs. Boffin would like an orphan who squints so much.”

“That’s true again,” said Mr. Milvey, becoming haggard with perplexity. “If a little girl would do—”

“But, my dear Frank, Mrs. Boffin wants a boy.”

“That’s true again,” said Mr. Milvey. “Tom Bocker is a nice boy,” (thoughtfully).

“But I doubt, Frank,” Mrs. Milvey hinted, after a little hesitation, “if Mrs. Boffin wants an orphan quite nineteen, who drives a cart and waters the roads.”

Mr. Milvey referred the point to Mrs. Boffin in a look; on that smiling lady’s shaking her black velvet bonnet and bows, he remarked, in lower spirits, “that’s true again.”

“I am sure,” said Mrs. Boffin, concerned at giving so much trouble, “that if I had known you would have taken so much pains, sir—and you too, ma’am—I don’t think I would have come.”

“Pray don’t say that!” urged Mrs. Milvey.

“No, don’t say that,” assented Mr. Milvey, “because we are so much obliged to you for giving us the preference.” Which Mrs. Milvey confirmed; and really the kind, conscientious couple spoke, as if they kept some profitable orphan warehouse and were personally patronized. “But it is a responsible trust,” added Mr. Milvey, “and difficult to discharge. At the same time, we are naturally very unwilling to lose the chance you so kindly give us, and if you could afford us a day or two to look about us—you know, Margaretta, we might carefully examine the workhouse, and the Infant School, and your District.”

“To be sure!” said the emphatic little wife.

“We have orphans, I know,” pursued Mr. Milvey, quite with the air as if he might have added, “in stock,” and quite as anxiously as if there were great competition in the business and he were afraid of losing an order, “over at the clay-pits; but they are employed by relations or friends, and I am afraid it would come at last to a transaction in the way of barter. And even if you exchanged blankets for the child—or books and firing—it would be impossible to prevent their being turned into liquor.”

Accordingly, it was resolved that Mr. and Mrs. Milvey should search for an orphan likely to suit, and as free as possible from the foregoing objections, and should communicate again with Mrs. Boffin. Then, Mr. Boffin took the liberty of mentioning to Mr. Milvey that if Mr. Milvey would do him the kindness to be perpetually his banker to the extent of “a twenty-pound note or so,” to be expended without any reference to him, he would be heartily obliged. At this, both Mr. Milvey and Mrs. Milvey were quite as much pleased as if they had no wants of their own, but only knew what poverty was, in the persons of other people; and so the interview terminated with satisfaction and good opinion on all sides.

“Now, old lady,” said Mr. Boffin, as they resumed their seats behind the hammer-headed horse and man: “having made a very agreeable visit there, we’ll try Wilfer’s.”

It appeared, on their drawing up at the family gate, that to try Wilfer’s was a thing more easily projected than done, on account of the extreme difficulty of getting into that establishment; three pulls at the bell producing no external result; though each was attended by audible sounds of scampering and rushing within. At the fourth tug—vindictively administered by the hammer-headed young man—Miss Lavinia appeared, emerging from the house in an accidental manner, with a bonnet and parasol, as designing to take a contemplative walk. The young lady was astonished to find visitors at the gate, and expressed her feelings in appropriate action.

“Here’s Mr. and Mrs. Boffin!” growled the hammer-headed young man through the bars of the gate, and at the same time shaking it, as if he were on view in a Menagerie; “they’ve been here half an hour.”

“Who did you say?” asked Miss Lavinia.

“Mr. and Mrs. Boffin” returned the young man, rising into a roar.

Miss Lavinia tripped up the steps to the house-door, tripped down the steps with the key, tripped across the little garden, and opened the gate. “Please to walk in,” said Miss Lavinia, haughtily. “Our servant is out.”

Mr. and Mrs. Boffin complying, and pausing in the little hall until Miss Lavinia came up to show them where to go next, perceived three pairs of listening legs upon the stairs above. Mrs. Wilfer’s legs, Miss Bella’s legs, Mr. George Sampson’s legs.

“Mr. and Mrs. Boffin, I think?” said Lavinia, in a warning voice. Strained attention on the part of Mrs. Wilfer’s legs, of Miss Bella’s legs, of Mr. George Sampson’s legs.

“Yes, Miss.”

“If you’ll step this way—down these stairs—I’ll let Ma know.” Excited flight of Mrs. Wilfer’s legs, of Miss Bella’s legs, of Mr. George Sampson’s legs.

After waiting some quarter of an hour alone in the family sitting-room, which presented traces of having been so hastily arranged after a meal, that one might have doubted whether it was made tidy for visitors, or cleared for blindman’s buff, Mr. and Mrs. Boffin became aware of the entrance of Mrs. Wilfer, majestically faint, and with a condescending stitch in her side: which was her company manner.

“Pardon me,” said Mrs. Wilfer, after the first salutations, and as soon as she had adjusted the handkerchief under her chin, and waved her gloved hands, “to what am I indebted for this honour?”

“To make short of it, ma’am,” returned Mr. Boffin, “perhaps you may be acquainted with the names of me and Mrs. Boffin, as having come into a certain property.”

“I have heard, sir,” returned Mrs. Wilfer, with a dignified bend of her head, “of such being the case.”

“And I dare say, ma’am,” pursued Mr. Boffin, while Mrs. Boffin added confirmatory nods and smiles, “you are not very much inclined to take kindly to us?”

“Pardon me,” said Mrs. Wilfer. “ ’Twere unjust to visit upon Mr. and Mrs. Boffin, a calamity which was doubtless a dispensation.” These words were rendered the more effective by a serenely heroic expression of suffering.

“That’s fairly meant, I am sure,” remarked the honest Mr. Boffin; “Mrs. Boffin and me, ma’am, are plain people, and we don’t want to pretend to anything, nor yet to go round and round at anything because there’s always a straight way to everything. Consequently, we make this call to say, that we shall be glad to have the honour and pleasure of your daughter’s acquaintance, and that we shall be rejoiced if your daughter will come to consider our house in the light of her home equally with this. In short, we want to cheer your daughter, and to give her the opportunity of sharing such pleasures as we are a going to take ourselves. We want to brisk her up, and brisk her about, and give her a change.”

“That’s it!” said the openhearted Mrs. Boffin. “Lor! Let’s be comfortable.”

Mrs. Wilfer bent her head in a distant manner to her lady visitor, and with majestic monotony replied to the gentleman:

“Pardon me. I have several daughters. Which of my daughters am I to understand is thus favoured by the kind intentions of Mr. Boffin and his lady?”

“Don’t you see?” the ever-smiling Mrs. Boffin put in. “Naturally, Miss Bella, you know.”

“Oh-h!” said Mrs. Wilfer, with a severely unconvinced look. “My daughter Bella is accessible and shall speak for herself.” Then opening the door a little way, simultaneously with a sound of scuttling outside it, the good lady made the proclamation, “Send Miss Bella to me!” which proclamation, though grandly formal, and one might almost say heraldic, to hear, was in fact enunciated with her maternal eyes reproachfully glaring on that young lady in the flesh—and in so much of it that she was retiring with difficulty into the small closet under the stairs, apprehensive of the emergence of Mr. and Mrs. Boffin.

“The avocations of R. W., my husband,” Mrs. Wilfer explained, on resuming her seat, “keep him fully engaged in the City at this time of the day, or he would have had the honour of participating in your reception beneath our humble roof.”

“Very pleasant premises!” said Mr. Boffin, cheerfully.

“Pardon me, sir,” returned Mrs. Wilfer, correcting him, “it is the abode of conscious though independent poverty.”

Finding it rather difficult to pursue the conversation down this road, Mr. and Mrs. Boffin sat staring at midair, and Mrs. Wilfer sat silently giving them to understand that every breath she drew required to be drawn with a self-denial rarely paralleled in history, until Miss Bella appeared: whom Mrs. Wilfer presented, and to whom she explained the purpose of the visitors.

“I am much obliged to you, I am sure,” said Miss Bella, coldly shaking her curls, “but I doubt if I have the inclination to go out at all.”

“Bella!” Mrs. Wilfer admonished her; “Bella, you must conquer this.”

“Yes, do what your Ma says, and conquer it, my dear,” urged Mrs. Boffin, “because we shall be so glad to have you, and because you are much too pretty to keep yourself shut up.” With that, the pleasant creature gave her a kiss, and patted her on her dimpled shoulders; Mrs. Wilfer sitting stiffly by, like a functionary presiding over an interview previous to an execution.

“We are going to move into a nice house,” said Mrs. Boffin, who was woman enough to compromise Mr. Boffin on that point, when he couldn’t very well contest it; “and we are going to set up a nice carriage, and we’ll go everywhere and see everything. And you mustn’t,” seating Bella beside her, and patting her hand, “you mustn’t feel a dislike to us to begin with, because we couldn’t help it, you know, my dear.”

With the natural tendency of youth to yield to candour and sweet temper, Miss Bella was so touched by the simplicity of this address that she frankly returned Mrs. Boffin’s kiss. Not at all to the satisfaction of that good woman of the world, her mother, who sought to hold the advantageous ground of obliging the Boffins instead of being obliged.

“My youngest daughter, Lavinia,” said Mrs. Wilfer, glad to make a diversion, as that young lady reappeared. “Mr. George Sampson, a friend of the family.”

The friend of the family was in that stage of tender passion which bound him to regard everybody else as the foe of the family. He put the round head of his cane in his mouth, like a stopper, when he sat down. As if he felt himself full to the throat with affronting sentiments. And he eyed the Boffins with implacable eyes.

“If you like to bring your sister with you when you come to stay with us,” said Mrs. Boffin, “of course we shall be glad. The better you please yourself, Miss Bella, the better you’ll please us.”

“Oh, my consent is of no consequence at all, I suppose?” cried Miss Lavinia.

“Lavvy,” said her sister, in a low voice, “have the goodness to be seen and not heard.”

“No, I won’t,” replied the sharp Lavinia. “I’m not a child, to be taken notice of by strangers.”

“You are a child.”

“I’m not a child, and I won’t be taken notice of. ‘Bring your sister,’ indeed!”

“Lavinia!” said Mrs. Wilfer. “Hold! I will not allow you to utter in my presence the absurd suspicion that any strangers—I care not what their names—can patronize my child. Do you dare to suppose, you ridiculous girl, that Mr. and Mrs. Boffin would enter these doors upon a patronizing errand; or, if they did, would remain within them, only for one single instant, while your mother had the strength yet remaining in her vital frame to request them to depart? You little know your mother if you presume to think so.”

“It’s all very fine,” Lavinia began to grumble, when Mrs. Wilfer repeated:

“Hold! I will not allow this. Do you not know what is due to guests? Do you not comprehend that in presuming to hint that this lady and gentleman could have any idea of patronizing any member of your family—I care not which—you accuse them of an impertinence little less than insane?”

“Never mind me and Mrs. Boffin, ma’am,” said Mr. Boffin, smilingly: “we don’t care.”

“Pardon me, but I do,” returned Mrs. Wilfer.

Miss Lavinia laughed a short laugh as she muttered, “Yes, to be sure.”

“And I require my audacious child,” proceeded Mrs. Wilfer, with a withering look at her youngest, on whom it had not the slightest effect, “to please to be just to her sister Bella; to remember that her sister Bella is much sought after; and that when her sister Bella accepts an attention, she considers herself to be conferring qui-i-ite as much honour,”—this with an indignant shiver—“as she receives.”

But, here Miss Bella repudiated, and said quietly, “I can speak for myself; you know, Ma. You needn’t bring me in, please.”

“And it’s all very well aiming at others through convenient me,” said the irrepressible Lavinia, spitefully; “but I should like to ask George Sampson what he says to it.”

“Mr. Sampson,” proclaimed Mrs. Wilfer, seeing that young gentleman take his stopper out, and so darkly fixing him with her eyes as that he put it in again: “Mr. Sampson, as a friend of this family and a frequenter of this house, is, I am persuaded, far too well-bred to interpose on such an invitation.”

This exaltation of the young gentleman moved the conscientious Mrs. Boffin to repentance for having done him an injustice in her mind, and consequently to saying that she and Mr. Boffin would at any time be glad to see him; an attention which he handsomely acknowledged by replying, with his stopper unremoved, “Much obliged to you, but I’m always engaged, day and night.”

However, Bella compensating for all drawbacks by responding to the advances of the Boffins in an engaging way, that easy pair were on the whole well satisfied, and proposed to the said Bella that as soon as they should be in a condition to receive her in a manner suitable to their desires, Mrs. Boffin should return with notice of the fact. This arrangement Mrs. Wilfer sanctioned with a stately inclination of her head and wave of her gloves, as who should say, “Your demerits shall be overlooked, and you shall be mercifully gratified, poor people.”

“By the by, ma’am,” said Mr. Boffin, turning back as he was going, “you have a lodger?”

“A gentleman,” Mrs. Wilfer answered, qualifying the low expression, “undoubtedly occupies our first floor.”

“I may call him Our Mutual Friend,” said Mr. Boffin. “What sort of a fellow is Our Mutual Friend, now? Do you like him?”

“Mr. Rokesmith is very punctual, very quiet, a very eligible inmate.”

“Because,” Mr. Boffin explained, “you must know that I’m not particularly well acquainted with Our Mutual Friend, for I have only seen him once. You give a good account of him. Is he at home?”

“Mr. Rokesmith is at home,” said Mrs. Wilfer; “indeed,” pointing through the window, “there he stands at the garden gate. Waiting for you, perhaps?”

“Perhaps so,” replied Mr. Boffin. “Saw me come in, maybe.”

Bella had closely attended to this short dialogue. Accompanying Mrs. Boffin to the gate, she as closely watched what followed.

“How are you, sir, how are you?” said Mr. Boffin. “This is Mrs. Boffin. Mr. Rokesmith, that I told you of; my dear.”

She gave him good day, and he bestirred himself and helped her to her seat, and the like, with a ready hand.

“Goodbye for the present, Miss Bella,” said Mrs. Boffin, calling out a hearty parting. “We shall meet again soon! And then I hope I shall have my little John Harmon to show you.”

Mr. Rokesmith, who was at the wheel adjusting the skirts of her dress, suddenly looked behind him, and around him, and then looked up at her, with a face so pale that Mrs. Boffin cried:

“Gracious!” And after a moment, “What’s the matter, sir?”

“How can you show her the dead?” returned Mr. Rokesmith.

“It’s only an adopted child. One I have told her of. One I’m going to give the name to!”

“You took me by surprise,” said Mr. Rokesmith, “and it sounded like an omen, that you should speak of showing the dead to one so young and blooming.”

Now, Bella suspected by this time that Mr. Rokesmith admired her. Whether the knowledge (for it was rather that than suspicion) caused her to incline to him a little more, or a little less, than she had done at first; whether it rendered her eager to find out more about him, because she sought to establish reason for her distrust, or because she sought to free him from it; was as yet dark to her own heart. But at most times he occupied a great amount of her attention, and she had set her attention closely on this incident.

That he knew it as well as she, she knew as well as he, when they were left together standing on the path by the garden gate.

“Those are worthy people, Miss Wilfer.”

“Do you know them well?” asked Bella.

He smiled, reproaching her, and she coloured, reproaching herself—both, with the knowledge that she had meant to entrap him into an answer not true—when he said “I know of them.”

“Truly, he told us he had seen you but once.”

“Truly, I supposed he did.”

Bella was nervous now, and would have been glad to recall her question.

“You thought it strange that, feeling much interested in you, I should start at what sounded like a proposal to bring you into contact with the murdered man who lies in his grave. I might have known—of course in a moment should have known—that it could not have that meaning. But my interest remains.”

Reentering the family-room in a meditative state, Miss Bella was received by the irrepressible Lavinia with:

“There, Bella! At last I hope you have got your wishes realized—by your Boffins. You’ll be rich enough now—with your Boffins. You can have as much flirting as you like—at your Boffins. But you won’t take me to your Boffins, I can tell you—you and your Boffins too!”

“If,” quoth Mr. George Sampson, moodily pulling his stopper out, “Miss Bella’s Mr. Boffin comes any more of his nonsense to me, I only wish him to understand, as betwixt man and man, that he does it at his per—” and was going to say peril; but Miss Lavinia, having no confidence in his mental powers, and feeling his oration to have no definite application to any circumstances, jerked his stopper in again, with a sharpness that made his eyes water.

And now the worthy Mrs. Wilfer, having used her youngest daughter as a lay-figure for the edification of these Boffins, became bland to her, and proceeded to develop her last instance of force of character, which was still in reserve. This was, to illuminate the family with her remarkable powers as a physiognomist; powers that terrified R. W. when ever let loose, as being always fraught with gloom and evil which no inferior prescience was aware of. And this Mrs. Wilfer now did, be it observed, in jealousy of these Boffins, in the very same moments when she was already reflecting how she would flourish these very same Boffins and the state they kept, over the heads of her Boffinless friends.

“Of their manners,” said Mrs. Wilfer, “I say nothing. Of their appearance, I say nothing. Of the disinterestedness of their intentions towards Bella, I say nothing. But the craft, the secrecy, the dark deep underhanded plotting, written in Mrs. Boffin’s countenance, make me shudder.”

As an incontrovertible proof that those baleful attributes were all there, Mrs. Wilfer shuddered on the spot.

XI

Podsnappery

Mr. Podsnap was well to do, and stood very high in Mr. Podsnap’s opinion. Beginning with a good inheritance, he had married a good inheritance, and had thriven exceedingly in the Marine Insurance way, and was quite satisfied. He never could make out why everybody was not quite satisfied, and he felt conscious that he set a brilliant social example in being particularly well satisfied with most things, and, above all other things, with himself.

Thus happily acquainted with his own merit and importance, Mr. Podsnap settled that whatever he put behind him he put out of existence. There was a dignified conclusiveness—not to add a grand convenience—in this way of getting rid of disagreeables which had done much towards establishing Mr. Podsnap in his lofty place in Mr. Podsnap’s satisfaction. “I don’t want to know about it; I don’t choose to discuss it; I don’t admit it!” Mr. Podsnap had even acquired a peculiar flourish of his right arm in often clearing the world of its most difficult problems, by sweeping them behind him (and consequently sheer away) with those words and a flushed face. For they affronted him.

Mr. Podsnap’s world was not a very large world, morally; no, nor even geographically: seeing that although his business was sustained upon commerce with other countries, he considered other countries, with that important reservation, a mistake, and of their manners and customs would conclusively observe, “Not English!” when, presto! with a flourish of the arm, and a flush of the face, they were swept away. Elsewise, the world got up at eight, shaved close at a quarter-past, breakfasted at nine, went to the City at ten, came home at half-past five, and dined at seven. Mr. Podsnap’s notions of the Arts in their integrity might have been stated thus. Literature; large print, respectfully descriptive of getting up at eight, shaving close at a quarter past, breakfasting at nine, going to the City at ten, coming home at half-past five, and dining at seven. Painting and sculpture; models and portraits representing professors of getting up at eight, shaving close at a quarter past, breakfasting at nine, going to the City at ten, coming home at half-past five, and dining at seven. Music; a respectable performance (without variations) on stringed and wind instruments, sedately expressive of getting up at eight, shaving close at a quarter past, breakfasting at nine, going to the City at ten, coming home at half-past five, and dining at seven. Nothing else to be permitted to those same vagrants the Arts, on pain of excommunication. Nothing else To Be—anywhere!

As a so eminently respectable man, Mr. Podsnap was sensible of its being required of him to take Providence under his protection. Consequently he always knew exactly what Providence meant. Inferior and less respectable men might fall short of that mark, but Mr. Podsnap was always up to it. And it was very remarkable (and must have been very comfortable) that what Providence meant, was invariably what Mr. Podsnap meant.

These may be said to have been the articles of a faith and school which the present chapter takes the liberty of calling, after its representative man, Podsnappery. They were confined within close bounds, as Mr. Podsnap’s own head was confined by his shirt-collar; and they were enunciated with a sounding pomp that smacked of the creaking of Mr. Podsnap’s own boots.

There was a Miss Podsnap. And this young rocking-horse was being trained in her mother’s art of prancing in a stately manner without ever getting on. But the high parental action was not yet imparted to her, and in truth she was but an undersized damsel, with high shoulders, low spirits, chilled elbows, and a rasped surface of nose, who seemed to take occasional frosty peeps out of childhood into womanhood, and to shrink back again, overcome by her mother’s headdress and her father from head to foot—crushed by the mere dead-weight of Podsnappery.

A certain institution in Mr. Podsnap’s mind which he called “the young person” may be considered to have been embodied in Miss Podsnap, his daughter. It was an inconvenient and exacting institution, as requiring everything in the universe to be filed down and fitted to it. The question about everything was, would it bring a blush into the cheek of the young person? And the inconvenience of the young person was, that, according to Mr. Podsnap, she seemed always liable to burst into blushes when there was no need at all. There appeared to be no line of demarcation between the young person’s excessive innocence, and another person’s guiltiest knowledge. Take Mr. Podsnap’s word for it, and the soberest tints of drab, white, lilac, and grey, were all flaming red to this troublesome bull of a young person.

The Podsnaps lived in a shady angle adjoining Portman Square. They were a kind of people certain to dwell in the shade, wherever they dwelt. Miss Podsnap’s life had been, from her first appearance on this planet, altogether of a shady order; for, Mr. Podsnap’s young person was likely to get little good out of association with other young persons, and had therefore been restricted to companionship with not very congenial older persons, and with massive furniture. Miss Podsnap’s early views of life being principally derived from the reflections of it in her father’s boots, and in the walnut and rosewood tables of the dim drawing-rooms, and in their swarthy giants of looking-glasses, were of a sombre cast; and it was not wonderful that now, when she was on most days solemnly tooled through the Park by the side of her mother in a great tall custard-coloured phaeton, she showed above the apron of that vehicle like a dejected young person sitting up in bed to take a startled look at things in general, and very strongly desiring to get her head under the counterpane again.

Said Mr. Podsnap to Mrs. Podsnap, “Georgiana is almost eighteen.”

Said Mrs. Podsnap to Mr. Podsnap, assenting, “Almost eighteen.”

Said Mr. Podsnap then to Mrs. Podsnap, “Really I think we should have some people on Georgiana’s birthday.”

Said Mrs. Podsnap then to Mr. Podsnap, “Which will enable us to clear off all those people who are due.”

So it came to pass that Mr. and Mrs. Podsnap requested the honour of the company of seventeen friends of their souls at dinner; and that they substituted other friends of their souls for such of the seventeen original friends of their souls as deeply regretted that a prior engagement prevented their having the honour of dining with Mr. and Mrs. Podsnap, in pursuance of their kind invitation; and that Mrs. Podsnap said of all these inconsolable personages, as she checked them off with a pencil in her list, “Asked, at any rate, and got rid of;” and that they successfully disposed of a good many friends of their souls in this way, and felt their consciences much lightened.

There were still other friends of their souls who were not entitled to be asked to dinner, but had a claim to be invited to come and take a haunch of mutton vapour-bath at half-past nine. For the clearing off of these worthies, Mrs. Podsnap added a small and early evening to the dinner, and looked in at the music-shop to bespeak a well-conducted automaton to come and play quadrilles for a carpet dance.

Mr. and Mrs. Veneering, and Mr. and Mrs. Veneering’s bran-new bride and bridegroom, were of the dinner company; but the Podsnap establishment had nothing else in common with the Veneerings. Mr. Podsnap could tolerate taste in a mushroom man who stood in need of that sort of thing, but was far above it himself. Hideous solidity was the characteristic of the Podsnap plate. Everything was made to look as heavy as it could, and to take up as much room as possible. Everything said boastfully, “Here you have as much of me in my ugliness as if I were only lead; but I am so many ounces of precious metal worth so much an ounce;—wouldn’t you like to melt me down?” A corpulent straddling epergne, blotched all over as if it had broken out in an eruption rather than been ornamented, delivered this address from an unsightly silver platform in the centre of the table. Four silver wine-coolers, each furnished with four staring heads, each head obtrusively carrying a big silver ring in each of its ears, conveyed the sentiment up and down the table, and handed it on to the potbellied silver saltcellars. All the big silver spoons and forks widened the mouths of the company expressly for the purpose of thrusting the sentiment down their throats with every morsel they ate.

The majority of the guests were like the plate, and included several heavy articles weighing ever so much. But there was a foreign gentleman among them: whom Mr. Podsnap had invited after much debate with himself—believing the whole European continent to be in mortal alliance against the young person—and there was a droll disposition, not only on the part of Mr. Podsnap but of everybody else, to treat him as if he were a child who was hard of hearing.

As a delicate concession to this unfortunately-born foreigner, Mr. Podsnap, in receiving him, had presented his wife as “Madame Podsnap;” also his daughter as “Mademoiselle Podsnap,” with some inclination to add “ma fille,” in which bold venture, however, he checked himself. The Veneerings being at that time the only other arrivals, he had added (in a condescendingly explanatory manner), “Monsieur Vey-nair-reeng,” and had then subsided into English.

“How Do You Like London?” Mr. Podsnap now inquired from his station of host, as if he were administering something in the nature of a powder or potion to the deaf child; “London, Londres, London?”

The foreign gentleman admired it.

“You find it Very Large?” said Mr. Podsnap, spaciously.

The foreign gentleman found it very large.

“And Very Rich?”

The foreign gentleman found it, without doubt, enormement riche.

“Enormously Rich, We say,” returned Mr. Podsnap, in a condescending manner. “Our English adverbs do Not terminate in Mong, and We Pronounce the ‘ch’ as if there were a ‘t’ before it. We say Ritch.”

“Reetch,” remarked the foreign gentleman.

“And Do You Find, Sir,” pursued Mr. Podsnap, with dignity, “Many Evidences that Strike You, of our British Constitution in the Streets Of The World’s Metropolis, London, Londres, London?”

The foreign gentleman begged to be pardoned, but did not altogether understand.

“The Constitution Britannique,” Mr. Podsnap explained, as if he were teaching in an infant school. “We Say British, But You Say Britannique, You Know,” (forgivingly, as if that were not his fault). “The Constitution, Sir.”

The foreign gentleman said, “Mais, yees; I know eem.”

A youngish sallowish gentleman in spectacles, with a lumpy forehead, seated in a supplementary chair at a corner of the table, here caused a profound sensation by saying, in a raised voice, “Esker,” and then stopping dead.

“Mais oui,” said the foreign gentleman, turning towards him. “Est-ce que? Quoi donc?”

But the gentleman with the lumpy forehead having for the time delivered himself of all that he found behind his lumps, spake for the time no more.

“I Was Inquiring,” said Mr. Podsnap, resuming the thread of his discourse, “Whether You Have Observed in our Streets as We should say, Upon our Pavvy as You would say, any Tokens—”

The foreign gentleman, with patient courtesy entreated pardon; “But what was tokenz?”

“Marks,” said Mr. Podsnap; “Signs, you know, Appearances—Traces.”

“Ah! Of a Orse?” inquired the foreign gentleman.

“We call it Horse,” said Mr. Podsnap, with forbearance. “In England, Angleterre, England, We Aspirate the ‘H,’ and We Say ‘Horse.’ Only our Lower Classes Say ‘Orse!’ ”

“Pardon,” said the foreign gentleman; “I am alwiz wrong!”

“Our Language,” said Mr. Podsnap, with a gracious consciousness of being always right, “is Difficult. Ours is a Copious Language, and Trying to Strangers. I will not Pursue my Question.”

But the lumpy gentleman, unwilling to give it up, again madly said, “Esker,” and again spake no more.

“It merely referred,” Mr. Podsnap explained, with a sense of meritorious proprietorship, “to Our Constitution, Sir. We Englishmen are Very Proud of our Constitution, Sir. It Was Bestowed Upon Us By Providence. No Other Country is so Favoured as This Country.”

“And ozer countries?—” the foreign gentleman was beginning, when Mr. Podsnap put him right again.

“We do not say Ozer; we say Other: the letters are ‘T’ and ‘H’; You say Tay and Aish, You Know; (still with clemency). The sound is ‘th’—‘th!’ ”

“And other countries,” said the foreign gentleman. “They do how?”

“They do, Sir,” returned Mr. Podsnap, gravely shaking his head; “they do—I am sorry to be obliged to say it—as they do.”

“It was a little particular of Providence,” said the foreign gentleman, laughing; “for the frontier is not large.”

“Undoubtedly,” assented Mr. Podsnap; “But So it is. It was the Charter of the Land. This Island was Blest, Sir, to the Direct Exclusion of such Other Countries as—as there may happen to be. And if we were all Englishmen present, I would say,” added Mr. Podsnap, looking round upon his compatriots, and sounding solemnly with his theme, “that there is in the Englishman a combination of qualities, a modesty, an independence, a responsibility, a repose, combined with an absence of everything calculated to call a blush into the cheek of a young person, which one would seek in vain among the Nations of the Earth.”

Having delivered this little summary, Mr. Podsnap’s face flushed, as he thought of the remote possibility of its being at all qualified by any prejudiced citizen of any other country; and, with his favourite right-arm flourish, he put the rest of Europe and the whole of Asia, Africa, and America nowhere.

The audience were much edified by this passage of words; and Mr. Podsnap, feeling that he was in rather remarkable force today, became smiling and conversational.

“Has anything more been heard, Veneering,” he inquired, “of the lucky legatee?”

“Nothing more,” returned Veneering, “than that he has come into possession of the property. I am told people now call him The Golden Dustman. I mentioned to you some time ago, I think, that the young lady whose intended husband was murdered is daughter to a clerk of mine?”

“Yes, you told me that,” said Podsnap; “and by the by, I wish you would tell it again here, for it’s a curious coincidence—curious that the first news of the discovery should have been brought straight to your table (when I was there), and curious that one of your people should have been so nearly interested in it. Just relate that, will you?”

Veneering was more than ready to do it, for he had prospered exceedingly upon the Harmon Murder, and had turned the social distinction it conferred upon him to the account of making several dozen of bran-new bosom-friends. Indeed, such another lucky hit would almost have set him up in that way to his satisfaction. So, addressing himself to the most desirable of his neighbours, while Mrs. Veneering secured the next most desirable, he plunged into the case, and emerged from it twenty minutes afterwards with a Bank Director in his arms. In the meantime, Mrs. Veneering had dived into the same waters for a wealthy Ship-Broker, and had brought him up, safe and sound, by the hair. Then Mrs. Veneering had to relate, to a larger circle, how she had been to see the girl, and how she was really pretty, and (considering her station) presentable. And this she did with such a successful display of her eight aquiline fingers and their encircling jewels, that she happily laid hold of a drifting General Officer, his wife and daughter, and not only restored their animation which had become suspended, but made them lively friends within an hour.

Although Mr. Podsnap would in a general way have highly disapproved of bodies in rivers as ineligible topics with reference to the cheek of the young person, he had, as one may say, a share in this affair which made him a part proprietor. As its returns were immediate, too, in the way of restraining the company from speechless contemplation of the wine-coolers, it paid, and he was satisfied.

And now the haunch of mutton vapour-bath having received a gamey infusion, and a few last touches of sweets and coffee, was quite ready, and the bathers came; but not before the discreet automaton had got behind the bars of the piano music-desk, and there presented the appearance of a captive languishing in a rosewood jail. And who now so pleasant or so well assorted as Mr. and Mrs. Alfred Lammle, he all sparkle, she all gracious contentment, both at occasional intervals exchanging looks like partners at cards who played a game against All England.

There was not much youth among the bathers, but there was no youth (the young person always excepted) in the articles of Podsnappery. Bald bathers folded their arms and talked to Mr. Podsnap on the hearthrug; sleek-whiskered bathers, with hats in their hands, lunged at Mrs. Podsnap and retreated; prowling bathers, went about looking into ornamental boxes and bowls as if they had suspicions of larceny on the part of the Podsnaps, and expected to find something they had lost at the bottom; bathers of the gentler sex sat silently comparing ivory shoulders. All this time and always, poor little Miss Podsnap, whose tiny efforts (if she had made any) were swallowed up in the magnificence of her mother’s rocking, kept herself as much out of sight and mind as she could, and appeared to be counting on many dismal returns of the day. It was somehow understood, as a secret article in the state proprieties of Podsnappery that nothing must be said about the day. Consequently this young damsel’s nativity was hushed up and looked over, as if it were agreed on all hands that it would have been better that she had never been born.

The Lammles were so fond of the dear Veneerings that they could not for some time detach themselves from those excellent friends; but at length, either a very open smile on Mr. Lammle’s part, or a very secret elevation of one of his gingerous eyebrows—certainly the one or the other—seemed to say to Mrs. Lammle, “Why don’t you play?” And so, looking about her, she saw Miss Podsnap, and seeming to say responsively, “That card?” and to be answered, “Yes,” went and sat beside Miss Podsnap.

Mrs. Lammle was overjoyed to escape into a corner for a little quiet talk.

It promised to be a very quiet talk, for Miss Podsnap replied in a flutter, “Oh! Indeed, it’s very kind of you, but I am afraid I don’t talk.”

“Let us make a beginning,” said the insinuating Mrs. Lammle, with her best smile.

“Oh! I am afraid you’ll find me very dull. But Ma talks!”

That was plainly to be seen, for Ma was talking then at her usual canter, with arched head and mane, opened eyes and nostrils.

“Fond of reading perhaps?”

“Yes. At least I—don’t mind that so much,” returned Miss Podsnap.

“M-m-m-m-music.” So insinuating was Mrs. Lammle that she got half a dozen ms into the word before she got it out.

“I haven’t nerve to play even if I could. Ma plays.”

(At exactly the same canter, and with a certain flourishing appearance of doing something, Ma did, in fact, occasionally take a rock upon the instrument.)

“Of course you like dancing?”

“Oh no, I don’t,” said Miss Podsnap.

“No? With your youth and attractions? Truly, my dear, you surprise me!”

“I can’t say,” observed Miss Podsnap, after hesitating considerably, and stealing several timid looks at Mrs. Lammle’s carefully arranged face, “how I might have liked it if I had been a—you won’t mention it, will you?”

“My dear! Never!”

“No, I am sure you won’t. I can’t say then how I should have liked it, if I had been a chimney-sweep on May-Day.”

“Gracious!” was the exclamation which amazement elicited from Mrs. Lammle.

“There! I knew you’d wonder. But you won’t mention it, will you?”

“Upon my word, my love,” said Mrs. Lammle, “you make me ten times more desirous, now I talk to you, to know you well than I was when I sat over yonder looking at you. How I wish we could be real friends! Try me as a real friend. Come! Don’t fancy me a frumpy old married woman, my dear; I was married but the other day, you know; I am dressed as a bride now, you see. About the chimney-sweeps?”

“Hush! Ma’ll hear.”

“She can’t hear from where she sits.”

“Don’t you be too sure of that,” said Miss Podsnap, in a lower voice. “Well, what I mean is, that they seem to enjoy it.”

“And that perhaps you would have enjoyed it, if you had been one of them?”

Miss Podsnap nodded significantly.

“Then you don’t enjoy it now?”

“How is it possible?” said Miss Podsnap. “Oh it is such a dreadful thing! If I was wicked enough—and strong enough—to kill anybody, it should be my partner.”

This was such an entirely new view of the Terpsichorean art as socially practised, that Mrs. Lammle looked at her young friend in some astonishment. Her young friend sat nervously twiddling her fingers in a pinioned attitude, as if she were trying to hide her elbows. But this latter Utopian object (in short sleeves) always appeared to be the great inoffensive aim of her existence.

“It sounds horrid, don’t it?” said Miss Podsnap, with a penitential face.

Mrs. Lammle, not very well knowing what to answer, resolved herself into a look of smiling encouragement.

“But it is, and it always has been,” pursued Miss Podsnap, “such a trial to me! I so dread being awful. And it is so awful! No one knows what I suffered at Madame Sauteuse’s, where I learnt to dance and make presentation-curtseys, and other dreadful things—or at least where they tried to teach me. Ma can do it.”

“At any rate, my love,” said Mrs. Lammle, soothingly, “that’s over.”

“Yes, it’s over,” returned Miss Podsnap, “but there’s nothing gained by that. It’s worse here, than at Madame Sauteuse’s. Ma was there, and Ma’s here; but Pa wasn’t there, and company wasn’t there, and there were not real partners there. Oh there’s Ma speaking to the man at the piano! Oh there’s Ma going up to somebody! Oh I know she’s going to bring him to me! Oh please don’t, please don’t, please don’t! Oh keep away, keep away, keep away!” These pious ejaculations Miss Podsnap uttered with her eyes closed, and her head leaning back against the wall.

But the Ogre advanced under the pilotage of Ma, and Ma said, “Georgiana, Mr. Grompus,” and the Ogre clutched his victim and bore her off to his castle in the top couple. Then the discreet automaton who had surveyed his ground, played a blossomless tuneless “set,” and sixteen disciples of Podsnappery went through the figures of - 1, Getting up at eight and shaving close at a quarter past - 2, Breakfasting at nine - 3, Going to the City at ten - 4, Coming home at half-past five - 5, Dining at seven, and the grand chain.

While these solemnities were in progress, Mr. Alfred Lammle (most loving of husbands) approached the chair of Mrs. Alfred Lammle (most loving of wives), and bending over the back of it, trifled for some few seconds with Mrs. Lammle’s bracelet. Slightly in contrast with this brief airy toying, one might have noticed a certain dark attention in Mrs. Lammle’s face as she said some words with her eyes on Mr. Lammle’s waistcoat, and seemed in return to receive some lesson. But it was all done as a breath passes from a mirror.

And now, the grand chain riveted to the last link, the discreet automaton ceased, and the sixteen, two and two, took a walk among the furniture. And herein the unconsciousness of the Ogre Grompus was pleasantly conspicuous; for, that complacent monster, believing that he was giving Miss Podsnap a treat, prolonged to the utmost stretch of possibility a peripatetic account of an archery meeting; while his victim, heading the procession of sixteen as it slowly circled about, like a revolving funeral, never raised her eyes except once to steal a glance at Mrs. Lammle, expressive of intense despair.

At length the procession was dissolved by the violent arrival of a nutmeg, before which the drawing-room door bounced open as if it were a cannonball; and while that fragrant article, dispersed through several glasses of coloured warm water, was going the round of society, Miss Podsnap returned to her seat by her new friend.

“Oh my goodness,” said Miss Podsnap. “that’s over! I hope you didn’t look at me.”

“My dear, why not?”

“Oh I know all about myself,” said Miss Podsnap.

“I’ll tell you something I know about you, my dear,” returned Mrs. Lammle in her winning way, “and that is, you are most unnecessarily shy.”

“Ma ain’t,” said Miss Podsnap. “—I detest you! Go along!” This shot was levelled under her breath at the gallant Grompus for bestowing an insinuating smile upon her in passing.

“Pardon me if I scarcely see, my dear Miss Podsnap,” Mrs. Lammle was beginning when the young lady interposed.

“If we are going to be real friends (and I suppose we are, for you are the only person who ever proposed it) don’t let us be awful. It’s awful enough to be Miss Podsnap, without being called so. Call me Georgiana.”

“Dearest Georgiana,” Mrs. Lammle began again.

“Thank you,” said Miss Podsnap.

“Dearest Georgiana, pardon me if I scarcely see, my love, why your mamma’s not being shy, is a reason why you should be.”

“Don’t you really see that?” asked Miss Podsnap, plucking at her fingers in a troubled manner, and furtively casting her eyes now on Mrs. Lammle, now on the ground. “Then perhaps it isn’t?”

“My dearest Georgiana, you defer much too readily to my poor opinion. Indeed it is not even an opinion, darling, for it is only a confession of my dullness.”

“Oh you are not dull,” returned Miss Podsnap. “I am dull, but you couldn’t have made me talk if you were.”

Some little touch of conscience answering this perception of her having gained a purpose, called bloom enough into Mrs. Lammle’s face to make it look brighter as she sat smiling her best smile on her dear Georgiana, and shaking her head with an affectionate playfulness. Not that it meant anything, but that Georgiana seemed to like it.

“What I mean is,” pursued Georgiana, “that Ma being so endowed with awfulness, and Pa being so endowed with awfulness, and there being so much awfulness everywhere—I mean, at least, everywhere where I am—perhaps it makes me who am so deficient in awfulness, and frightened at it—I say it very badly—I don’t know whether you can understand what I mean?”

“Perfectly, dearest Georgiana!” Mrs. Lammle was proceeding with every reassuring wile, when the head of that young lady suddenly went back against the wall again and her eyes closed.

“Oh there’s Ma being awful with somebody with a glass in his eye! Oh I know she’s going to bring him here! Oh don’t bring him, don’t bring him! Oh he’ll be my partner with his glass in his eye! Oh what shall I do!” This time Georgiana accompanied her ejaculations with taps of her feet upon the floor, and was altogether in quite a desperate condition. But, there was no escape from the majestic Mrs. Podsnap’s production of an ambling stranger, with one eye screwed up into extinction and the other framed and glazed, who, having looked down out of that organ, as if he descried Miss Podsnap at the bottom of some perpendicular shaft, brought her to the surface, and ambled off with her. And then the captive at the piano played another “set,” expressive of his mournful aspirations after freedom, and other sixteen went through the former melancholy motions, and the ambler took Miss Podsnap for a furniture walk, as if he had struck out an entirely original conception.

In the meantime a stray personage of a meek demeanour, who had wandered to the hearthrug and got among the heads of tribes assembled there in conference with Mr. Podsnap, eliminated Mr. Podsnap’s flush and flourish by a highly unpolite remark; no less than a reference to the circumstance that some half-dozen people had lately died in the streets, of starvation. It was clearly ill-timed after dinner. It was not adapted to the cheek of the young person. It was not in good taste.

“I don’t believe it,” said Mr. Podsnap, putting it behind him.

The meek man was afraid we must take it as proved, because there were the inquests and the Registrar’s returns.

“Then it was their own fault,” said Mr. Podsnap.

Veneering and other elders of tribes commended this way out of it. At once a shortcut and a broad road.

The man of meek demeanour intimated that truly it would seem from the facts, as if starvation had been forced upon the culprits in question—as if, in their wretched manner, they had made their weak protests against it—as if they would have taken the liberty of staving it off if they could—as if they would rather not have been starved upon the whole, if perfectly agreeable to all parties.

“There is not,” said Mr. Podsnap, flushing angrily, “there is not a country in the world, sir, where so noble a provision is made for the poor as in this country.”

The meek man was quite willing to concede that, but perhaps it rendered the matter even worse, as showing that there must be something appallingly wrong somewhere.

“Where?” said Mr. Podsnap.

The meek man hinted wouldn’t it be well to try, very seriously, to find out where?

“Ah!” said Mr. Podsnap. “Easy to say somewhere; not so easy to say where! But I see what you are driving at. I knew it from the first. Centralization. No. Never with my consent. Not English.”

An approving murmur arose from the heads of tribes; as saying, “There you have him! Hold him!”

He was not aware (the meek man submitted of himself) that he was driving at any ization. He had no favourite ization that he knew of. But he certainly was more staggered by these terrible occurrences than he was by names, of howsoever so many syllables. Might he ask, was dying of destitution and neglect necessarily English?

“You know what the population of London is, I suppose,” said Mr. Podsnap.

The meek man supposed he did, but supposed that had absolutely nothing to do with it, if its laws were well administered.

“And you know; at least I hope you know;” said Mr. Podsnap, with severity, “that Providence has declared that you shall have the poor always with you?”

The meek man also hoped he knew that.

“I am glad to hear it,” said Mr. Podsnap with a portentous air. “I am glad to hear it. It will render you cautious how you fly in the face of Providence.”

In reference to that absurd and irreverent conventional phrase, the meek man said, for which Mr. Podsnap was not responsible, he the meek man had no fear of doing anything so impossible; but—

But Mr. Podsnap felt that the time had come for flushing and flourishing this meek man down for good. So he said:

“I must decline to pursue this painful discussion. It is not pleasant to my feelings; it is repugnant to my feelings. I have said that I do not admit these things. I have also said that if they do occur (not that I admit it), the fault lies with the sufferers themselves. It is not for me”—Mr. Podsnap pointed “me” forcibly, as adding by implication though it may be all very well for you—“it is not for me to impugn the workings of Providence. I know better than that, I trust, and I have mentioned what the intentions of Providence are. Besides,” said Mr. Podsnap, flushing high up among his hairbrushes, with a strong consciousness of personal affront, “the subject is a very disagreeable one. I will go so far as to say it is an odious one. It is not one to be introduced among our wives and young persons, and I—” He finished with that flourish of his arm which added more expressively than any words, And I remove it from the face of the earth.

Simultaneously with this quenching of the meek man’s ineffectual fire; Georgiana having left the ambler up a lane of sofa, in a No Thoroughfare of back drawing-room, to find his own way out, came back to Mrs. Lammle. And who should be with Mrs. Lammle, but Mr. Lammle. So fond of her!

“Alfred, my love, here is my friend. Georgiana, dearest girl, you must like my husband next to me.”

Mr. Lammle was proud to be so soon distinguished by this special commendation to Miss Podsnap’s favour. But if Mr. Lammle were prone to be jealous of his dear Sophronia’s friendships, he would be jealous of her feeling towards Miss Podsnap.

“Say Georgiana, darling,” interposed his wife.

“Towards—shall I?—Georgiana.” Mr. Lammle uttered the name, with a delicate curve of his right hand, from his lips outward. “For never have I known Sophronia (who is not apt to take sudden likings) so attracted and so captivated as she is by—shall I once more?—Georgiana.”

The object of this homage sat uneasily enough in receipt of it, and then said, turning to Mrs. Lammle, much embarrassed:

“I wonder what you like me for! I am sure I can’t think.”

“Dearest Georgiana, for yourself. For your difference from all around you.”

“Well! That may be. For I think I like you for your difference from all around me,” said Georgiana with a smile of relief.

“We must be going with the rest,” observed Mrs. Lammle, rising with a show of unwillingness, amidst a general dispersal. “We are real friends, Georgiana dear?”

“Real.”

“Good night, dear girl!”

She had established an attraction over the shrinking nature upon which her smiling eyes were fixed, for Georgiana held her hand while she answered in a secret and half-frightened tone:

“Don’t forget me when you are gone away. And come again soon. Good night!”

Charming to see Mr. and Mrs. Lammle taking leave so gracefully, and going down the stairs so lovingly and sweetly. Not quite so charming to see their smiling faces fall and brood as they dropped moodily into separate corners of their little carriage. But to be sure that was a sight behind the scenes, which nobody saw, and which nobody was meant to see.

Certain big, heavy vehicles, built on the model of the Podsnap plate, took away the heavy articles of guests weighing ever so much; and the less valuable articles got away after their various manners; and the Podsnap plate was put to bed. As Mr. Podsnap stood with his back to the drawing-room fire, pulling up his shirt-collar, like a veritable cock of the walk literally pluming himself in the midst of his possessions, nothing would have astonished him more than an intimation that Miss Podsnap, or any other young person properly born and bred, could not be exactly put away like the plate, brought out like the plate, polished like the plate, counted, weighed, and valued like the plate. That such a young person could possibly have a morbid vacancy in the heart for anything younger than the plate, or less monotonous than the plate; or that such a young person’s thoughts could try to scale the region bounded on the north, south, east, and west, by the plate; was a monstrous imagination which he would on the spot have flourished into space. This perhaps in some sort arose from Mr. Podsnap’s blushing young person being, so to speak, all cheek; whereas there is a possibility that there may be young persons of a rather more complex organization.

If Mr. Podsnap, pulling up his shirt-collar, could only have heard himself called “that fellow” in a certain short dialogue, which passed between Mr. and Mrs. Lammle in their opposite corners of their little carriage, rolling home!

“Sophronia, are you awake?”

“Am I likely to be asleep, sir?”

“Very likely, I should think, after that fellow’s company. Attend to what I am going to say.”

“I have attended to what you have already said, have I not? What else have I been doing all tonight.”

“Attend, I tell you,” (in a raised voice) “to what I am going to say. Keep close to that idiot girl. Keep her under your thumb. You have her fast, and you are not to let her go. Do you hear?”

“I hear you.”

“I foresee there is money to be made out of this, besides taking that fellow down a peg. We owe each other money, you know.”

Mrs. Lammle winced a little at the reminder, but only enough to shake her scents and essences anew into the atmosphere of the little carriage, as she settled herself afresh in her own dark corner.

XV

Two New Servants

Mr. and Mrs. Boffin sat after breakfast, in the Bower, a prey to prosperity. Mr. Boffin’s face denoted care and complication. Many disordered papers were before him, and he looked at them about as hopefully as an innocent civilian might look at a crowd of troops whom he was required at five minutes’ notice to manoeuvre and review. He had been engaged in some attempts to make notes of these papers; but being troubled (as men of his stamp often are) with an exceedingly distrustful and corrective thumb, that busy member had so often interposed to smear his notes, that they were little more legible than the various impressions of itself; which blurred his nose and forehead. It is curious to consider, in such a case as Mr. Boffin’s, what a cheap article ink is, and how far it may be made to go. As a grain of musk will scent a drawer for many years, and still lose nothing appreciable of its original weight, so a halfpennyworth of ink would blot Mr. Boffin to the roots of his hair and the calves of his legs, without inscribing a line on the paper before him, or appearing to diminish in the inkstand.

Mr. Boffin was in such severe literary difficulties that his eyes were prominent and fixed, and his breathing was stertorous, when, to the great relief of Mrs. Boffin, who observed these symptoms with alarm, the yard bell rang.

“Who’s that, I wonder!” said Mrs. Boffin.

Mr. Boffin drew a long breath, laid down his pen, looked at his notes as doubting whether he had the pleasure of their acquaintance, and appeared, on a second perusal of their countenances, to be confirmed in his impression that he had not, when there was announced by the hammer-headed young man:

“Mr. Rokesmith.”

“Oh!” said Mr. Boffin. “Oh indeed! Our and the Wilfers’ Mutual Friend, my dear. Yes. Ask him to come in.”

Mr. Rokesmith appeared.

“Sit down, sir,” said Mr. Boffin, shaking hands with him. “Mrs. Boffin you’re already acquainted with. Well, sir, I am rather unprepared to see you, for, to tell you the truth, I’ve been so busy with one thing and another, that I’ve not had time to turn your offer over.”

“That’s apology for both of us: for Mr. Boffin, and for me as well,” said the smiling Mrs. Boffin. “But Lor! we can talk it over now; can’t us?”

Mr. Rokesmith bowed, thanked her, and said he hoped so.

“Let me see then,” resumed Mr. Boffin, with his hand to his chin. “It was Secretary that you named; wasn’t it?”

“I said Secretary,” assented Mr. Rokesmith.

“It rather puzzled me at the time,” said Mr. Boffin, “and it rather puzzled me and Mrs. Boffin when we spoke of it afterwards, because (not to make a mystery of our belief) we have always believed a Secretary to be a piece of furniture, mostly of mahogany, lined with green baize or leather, with a lot of little drawers in it. Now, you won’t think I take a liberty when I mention that you certainly ain’t that.”

Certainly not, said Mr. Rokesmith. But he had used the word in the sense of Steward.

“Why, as to Steward, you see,” returned Mr. Boffin, with his hand still to his chin, “the odds are that Mrs. Boffin and me may never go upon the water. Being both bad sailors, we should want a Steward if we did; but there’s generally one provided.”

Mr. Rokesmith again explained; defining the duties he sought to undertake, as those of general superintendent, or manager, or overlooker, or man of business.

“Now, for instance—come!” said Mr. Boffin, in his pouncing way. “If you entered my employment, what would you do?”

“I would keep exact accounts of all the expenditure you sanctioned, Mr. Boffin. I would write your letters, under your direction. I would transact your business with people in your pay or employment. I would,” with a glance and a half-smile at the table, “arrange your papers—”

Mr. Boffin rubbed his inky ear, and looked at his wife.

“—And so arrange them as to have them always in order for immediate reference, with a note of the contents of each outside it.”

“I tell you what,” said Mr. Boffin, slowly crumpling his own blotted note in his hand; “if you’ll turn to at these present papers, and see what you can make of ’em, I shall know better what I can make of you.”

No sooner said than done. Relinquishing his hat and gloves, Mr. Rokesmith sat down quietly at the table, arranged the open papers into an orderly heap, cast his eyes over each in succession, folded it, docketed it on the outside, laid it in a second heap, and, when that second heap was complete and the first gone, took from his pocket a piece of string and tied it together with a remarkably dexterous hand at a running curve and a loop.

“Good!” said Mr. Boffin. “Very good! Now let us hear what they’re all about; will you be so good?”

John Rokesmith read his abstracts aloud. They were all about the new house. Decorator’s estimate, so much. Furniture estimate, so much. Estimate for furniture of offices, so much. Coach-maker’s estimate, so much. Horse-dealer’s estimate, so much. Harness-maker’s estimate, so much. Goldsmith’s estimate, so much. Total, so very much. Then came correspondence. Acceptance of Mr. Boffin’s offer of such a date, and to such an effect. Rejection of Mr. Boffin’s proposal of such a date and to such an effect. Concerning Mr. Boffin’s scheme of such another date to such another effect. All compact and methodical.

“Apple-pie order!” said Mr. Boffin, after checking off each inscription with his hand, like a man beating time. “And whatever you do with your ink, I can’t think, for you’re as clean as a whistle after it. Now, as to a letter. Let’s,” said Mr. Boffin, rubbing his hands in his pleasantly childish admiration, “let’s try a letter next.”

“To whom shall it be addressed, Mr. Boffin?”

“Anyone. Yourself.”

Mr. Rokesmith quickly wrote, and then read aloud:

“ ‘Mr. Boffin presents his compliments to Mr. John Rokesmith, and begs to say that he has decided on giving Mr. John Rokesmith a trial in the capacity he desires to fill. Mr. Boffin takes Mr. John Rokesmith at his word, in postponing to some indefinite period, the consideration of salary. It is quite understood that Mr. Boffin is in no way committed on that point. Mr. Boffin has merely to add, that he relies on Mr. John Rokesmith’s assurance that he will be faithful and serviceable. Mr. John Rokesmith will please enter on his duties immediately.’ ”

“Well! Now, Noddy!” cried Mrs. Boffin, clapping her hands, “That is a good one!”

Mr. Boffin was no less delighted; indeed, in his own bosom, he regarded both the composition itself and the device that had given birth to it, as a very remarkable monument of human ingenuity.

“And I tell you, my deary,” said Mrs. Boffin, “that if you don’t close with Mr. Rokesmith now at once, and if you ever go a muddling yourself again with things never meant nor made for you, you’ll have an apoplexy—besides iron-moulding your linen—and you’ll break my heart.”

Mr. Boffin embraced his spouse for these words of wisdom, and then, congratulating John Rokesmith on the brilliancy of his achievements, gave him his hand in pledge of their new relations. So did Mrs. Boffin.

“Now,” said Mr. Boffin, who, in his frankness, felt that it did not become him to have a gentleman in his employment five minutes, without reposing some confidence in him, “you must be let a little more into our affairs, Rokesmith. I mentioned to you, when I made your acquaintance, or I might better say when you made mine, that Mrs. Boffin’s inclinations was setting in the way of Fashion, but that I didn’t know how fashionable we might or might not grow. Well! Mrs. Boffin has carried the day, and we’re going in neck and crop for Fashion.”

“I rather inferred that, sir,” replied John Rokesmith, “from the scale on which your new establishment is to be maintained.”

“Yes,” said Mr. Boffin, “it’s to be a spanker. The fact is, my literary man named to me that a house with which he is, as I may say, connected—in which he has an interest—”

“As property?” inquired John Rokesmith.

“Why no,” said Mr. Boffin, “not exactly that; a sort of a family tie.”

“Association?” the Secretary suggested.

“Ah!” said Mr. Boffin. “Perhaps. Anyhow, he named to me that the house had a board up, ‘This Eminently Aristocratic Mansion to be let or sold.’ Me and Mrs. Boffin went to look at it, and finding it beyond a doubt eminently aristocratic (though a trifle high and dull, which after all may be part of the same thing) took it. My literary man was so friendly as to drop into a charming piece of poetry on that occasion, in which he complimented Mrs. Boffin on coming into possession of—how did it go, my dear?”

Mrs. Boffin replied:

“ ‘The gay, the gay and festive scene,
The halls, the halls of dazzling light.’ ”

“That’s it! And it was made neater by there really being two halls in the house, a front ’un and a back ’un, besides the servants.” He likewise dropped into a very pretty piece of poetry to be sure, respecting the extent to which he would be willing to put himself out of the way to bring Mrs. Boffin round, in case she should ever get low in her spirits in the house. Mrs. Boffin has a wonderful memory. Will you repeat it, my dear?”

Mrs. Boffin complied, by reciting the verses in which this obliging offer had been made, exactly as she had received them.

“ ‘I’ll tell thee how the maiden wept, Mrs. Boffin,
When her true love was slain ma’am,
And how her broken spirit slept, Mrs. Boffin,
And never woke again ma’am.
I’ll tell thee (if agreeable to Mr. Boffin) how the steed drew nigh,
And left his lord afar;
And if my tale (which I hope Mr. Boffin might excuse) should make you sigh,
I’ll strike the light guitar.’ ”

“Correct to the letter!” said Mr. Boffin. “And I consider that the poetry brings us both in, in a beautiful manner.”

The effect of the poem on the Secretary being evidently to astonish him, Mr. Boffin was confirmed in his high opinion of it, and was greatly pleased.

“Now, you see, Rokesmith,” he went on, “a literary man—with a wooden leg—is liable to jealousy. I shall therefore cast about for comfortable ways and means of not calling up Wegg’s jealousy, but of keeping you in your department, and keeping him in his.”

“Lor!” cried Mrs. Boffin. “What I say is, the world’s wide enough for all of us!”

“So it is, my dear,” said Mr. Boffin, “when not literary. But when so, not so. And I am bound to bear in mind that I took Wegg on, at a time when I had no thought of being fashionable or of leaving the Bower. To let him feel himself anyways slighted now, would be to be guilty of a meanness, and to act like having one’s head turned by the halls of dazzling light. Which Lord forbid! Rokesmith, what shall we say about your living in the house?”

“In this house?”

“No, no. I have got other plans for this house. In the new house?”

“That will be as you please, Mr. Boffin. I hold myself quite at your disposal. You know where I live at present.”

“Well!” said Mr. Boffin, after considering the point; “suppose you keep as you are for the present, and we’ll decide by-and-by. You’ll begin to take charge at once, of all that’s going on in the new house, will you?”

“Most willingly. I will begin this very day. Will you give me the address?”

Mr. Boffin repeated it, and the Secretary wrote it down in his pocketbook. Mrs. Boffin took the opportunity of his being so engaged, to get a better observation of his face than she had yet taken. It impressed her in his favour, for she nodded aside to Mr. Boffin, “I like him.”

“I will see directly that everything is in train, Mr. Boffin.”

“Thank’ee. Being here, would you care at all to look round the Bower?”

“I should greatly like it. I have heard so much of its story.”

“Come!” said Mr. Boffin. And he and Mrs. Boffin led the way.

A gloomy house the Bower, with sordid signs on it of having been, through its long existence as Harmony Jail, in miserly holding. Bare of paint, bare of paper on the walls, bare of furniture, bare of experience of human life. Whatever is built by man for man’s occupation, must, like natural creations, fulfil the intention of its existence, or soon perish. This old house had wasted—more from desuetude than it would have wasted from use, twenty years for one.

A certain leanness falls upon houses not sufficiently imbued with life (as if they were nourished upon it), which was very noticeable here. The staircase, balustrades, and rails, had a spare look—an air of being denuded to the bone—which the panels of the walls and the jambs of the doors and windows also bore. The scanty moveables partook of it; save for the cleanliness of the place, the dust—into which they were all resolving would have lain thick on the floors; and those, both in colour and in grain, were worn like old faces that had kept much alone.

The bedroom where the clutching old man had lost his grip on life, was left as he had left it. There was the old grisly four-post bedstead, without hangings, and with a jail-like upper rim of iron and spikes; and there was the old patchwork counterpane. There was the tight-clenched old bureau, receding atop like a bad and secret forehead; there was the cumbersome old table with twisted legs, at the bedside; and there was the box upon it, in which the will had lain. A few old chairs with patchwork covers, under which the more precious stuff to be preserved had slowly lost its quality of colour without imparting pleasure to any eye, stood against the wall. A hard family likeness was on all these things.

“The room was kept like this, Rokesmith,” said Mr. Boffin, “against the son’s return. In short, everything in the house was kept exactly as it came to us, for him to see and approve. Even now, nothing is changed but our own room below-stairs that you have just left. When the son came home for the last time in his life, and for the last time in his life saw his father, it was most likely in this room that they met.”

As the Secretary looked all round it, his eyes rested on a side door in a corner.

“Another staircase,” said Mr. Boffin, unlocking the door, “leading down into the yard. We’ll go down this way, as you may like to see the yard, and it’s all in the road. When the son was a little child, it was up and down these stairs that he mostly came and went to his father. He was very timid of his father. I’ve seen him sit on these stairs, in his shy way, poor child, many a time. Mr. and Mrs. Boffin have comforted him, sitting with his little book on these stairs, often.”

“Ah! And his poor sister too,” said Mrs. Boffin. “And here’s the sunny place on the white wall where they one day measured one another. Their own little hands wrote up their names here, only with a pencil; but the names are here still, and the poor dears gone forever.”

“We must take care of the names, old lady,” said Mr. Boffin. “We must take care of the names. They shan’t be rubbed out in our time, nor yet, if we can help it, in the time after us. Poor little children!”

“Ah, poor little children!” said Mrs. Boffin.

They had opened the door at the bottom of the staircase giving on the yard, and they stood in the sunlight, looking at the scrawl of the two unsteady childish hands two or three steps up the staircase. There was something in this simple memento of a blighted childhood, and in the tenderness of Mrs. Boffin, that touched the Secretary.

Mr. Boffin then showed his new man of business the mounds, and his own particular mound which had been left him as his legacy under the will before he acquired the whole estate.

“It would have been enough for us,” said Mr. Boffin, “in case it had pleased God to spare the last of those two young lives and sorrowful deaths. We didn’t want the rest.”

At the treasures of the yard, and at the outside of the house, and at the detached building which Mr. Boffin pointed out as the residence of himself and his wife during the many years of their service, the Secretary looked with interest. It was not until Mr. Boffin had shown him every wonder of the Bower twice over, that he remembered his having duties to discharge elsewhere.

“You have no instructions to give me, Mr. Boffin, in reference to this place?”

“Not any, Rokesmith. No.”

“Might I ask, without seeming impertinent, whether you have any intention of selling it?”

“Certainly not. In remembrance of our old master, our old master’s children, and our old service, me and Mrs. Boffin mean to keep it up as it stands.”

The Secretary’s eyes glanced with so much meaning in them at the mounds, that Mr. Boffin said, as if in answer to a remark:

“Ay, ay, that’s another thing. I may sell them, though I should be sorry to see the neighbourhood deprived of ’em too. It’ll look but a poor dead flat without the mounds. Still I don’t say that I’m going to keep ’em always there, for the sake of the beauty of the landscape. There’s no hurry about it; that’s all I say at present. I ain’t a scholar in much, Rokesmith, but I’m a pretty fair scholar in dust. I can price the mounds to a fraction, and I know how they can be best disposed of; and likewise that they take no harm by standing where they do. You’ll look in tomorrow, will you be so kind?”

“Every day. And the sooner I can get you into your new house, complete, the better you will be pleased, sir?”

“Well, it ain’t that I’m in a mortal hurry,” said Mr. Boffin; “only when you do pay people for looking alive, it’s as well to know that they are looking alive. Ain’t that your opinion?”

“Quite!” replied the Secretary; and so withdrew.

“Now,” said Mr. Boffin to himself; subsiding into his regular series of turns in the yard, “if I can make it comfortable with Wegg, my affairs will be going smooth.”

The man of low cunning had, of course, acquired a mastery over the man of high simplicity. The mean man had, of course, got the better of the generous man. How long such conquests last, is another matter; that they are achieved, is everyday experience, not even to be flourished away by Podsnappery itself. The undesigning Boffin had become so far immeshed by the wily Wegg that his mind misgave him he was a very designing man indeed in purposing to do more for Wegg. It seemed to him (so skilful was Wegg) that he was plotting darkly, when he was contriving to do the very thing that Wegg was plotting to get him to do. And thus, while he was mentally turning the kindest of kind faces on Wegg this morning, he was not absolutely sure but that he might somehow deserve the charge of turning his back on him.

For these reasons Mr. Boffin passed but anxious hours until evening came, and with it Mr. Wegg, stumping leisurely to the Roman Empire. At about this period Mr. Boffin had become profoundly interested in the fortunes of a great military leader known to him as Bully Sawyers, but perhaps better known to fame and easier of identification by the classical student, under the less Britannic name of Belisarius. Even this general’s career paled in interest for Mr. Boffin before the clearing of his conscience with Wegg; and hence, when that literary gentleman had according to custom eaten and drunk until he was all aglow, and when he took up his book with the usual chirping introduction, “And now, Mr. Boffin, sir, we’ll decline and we’ll fall!” Mr. Boffin stopped him.

“You remember, Wegg, when I first told you that I wanted to make a sort of offer to you?”

“Let me get on my considering cap, sir,” replied that gentleman, turning the open book face downward. “When you first told me that you wanted to make a sort of offer to me? Now let me think.” (as if there were the least necessity) “Yes, to be sure I do, Mr. Boffin. It was at my corner. To be sure it was! You had first asked me whether I liked your name, and candour had compelled a reply in the negative case. I little thought then, sir, how familiar that name would come to be!”

“I hope it will be more familiar still, Wegg.”

“Do you, Mr. Boffin? Much obliged to you, I’m sure. Is it your pleasure, sir, that we decline and we fall?” with a feint of taking up the book.

“Not just yet awhile, Wegg. In fact, I have got another offer to make you.”

Mr. Wegg (who had had nothing else in his mind for several nights) took off his spectacles with an air of bland surprise.

“And I hope you’ll like it, Wegg.”

“Thank you, sir,” returned that reticent individual. “I hope it may prove so. On all accounts, I am sure.” (This, as a philanthropic aspiration.)

“What do you think,” said Mr. Boffin, “of not keeping a stall, Wegg?”

“I think, sir,” replied Wegg, “that I should like to be shown the gentleman prepared to make it worth my while!”

“Here he is,” said Mr. Boffin.

Mr. Wegg was going to say, My Benefactor, and had said My Bene, when a grandiloquent change came over him.

“No, Mr. Boffin, not you sir. Anybody but you. Do not fear, Mr. Boffin, that I shall contaminate the premises which your gold has bought, with my lowly pursuits. I am aware, sir, that it would not become me to carry on my little traffic under the windows of your mansion. I have already thought of that, and taken my measures. No need to be bought out, sir. Would Stepney Fields be considered intrusive? If not remote enough, I can go remoter. In the words of the poet’s song, which I do not quite remember:

Thrown on the wide world, doom’d to wander and roam,
Bereft of my parents, bereft of a home,
A stranger to something and what’s his name joy,
Behold little Edmund the poor peasant boy.

—And equally,” said Mr. Wegg, repairing the want of direct application in the last line, “behold myself on a similar footing!”

“Now, Wegg, Wegg, Wegg,” remonstrated the excellent Boffin. “You are too sensitive.”

“I know I am, sir,” returned Wegg, with obstinate magnanimity. “I am acquainted with my faults. I always was, from a child, too sensitive.”

“But listen,” pursued the Golden Dustman; “hear me out, Wegg. You have taken it into your head that I mean to pension you off.”

“True, sir,” returned Wegg, still with an obstinate magnanimity. “I am acquainted with my faults. Far be it from me to deny them. I have taken it into my head.”

“But I don’t mean it.”

The assurance seemed hardly as comforting to Mr. Wegg, as Mr. Boffin intended it to be. Indeed, an appreciable elongation of his visage might have been observed as he replied:

“Don’t you, indeed, sir?”

“No,” pursued Mr. Boffin; “because that would express, as I understand it, that you were not going to do anything to deserve your money. But you are; you are.”

“That, sir,” replied Mr. Wegg, cheering up bravely, “is quite another pair of shoes. Now, my independence as a man is again elevated. Now, I no longer

Weep for the hour,
When to Boffinses bower,
The Lord of the valley with offers came;
Neither does the moon hide her light
From the heavens tonight,
And weep behind her clouds o’er any individual in the present company’s shame.

—Please to proceed, Mr. Boffin.”

“Thank’ee, Wegg, both for your confidence in me and for your frequent dropping into poetry; both of which is friendly. Well, then; my idea is, that you should give up your stall, and that I should put you into the Bower here, to keep it for us. It’s a pleasant spot; and a man with coals and candles and a pound a week might be in clover here.”

“Hem! Would that man, sir—we will say that man, for the purposes of argueyment;” Mr. Wegg made a smiling demonstration of great perspicuity here; “would that man, sir, be expected to throw any other capacity in, or would any other capacity be considered extra? Now let us (for the purposes of argueyment) suppose that man to be engaged as a reader: say (for the purposes of argueyment) in the evening. Would that man’s pay as a reader in the evening, be added to the other amount, which, adopting your language, we will call clover; or would it merge into that amount, or clover?”

“Well,” said Mr. Boffin, “I suppose it would be added.”

“I suppose it would, sir. You are right, sir. Exactly my own views, Mr. Boffin.” Here Wegg rose, and balancing himself on his wooden leg, fluttered over his prey with extended hand. “Mr. Boffin, consider it done. Say no more, sir, not a word more. My stall and I are forever parted. The collection of ballads will in future be reserved for private study, with the object of making poetry tributary,”—Wegg was so proud of having found this word, that he said it again, with a capital letter—“Tributary, to friendship. Mr. Boffin, don’t allow yourself to be made uncomfortable by the pang it gives me to part from my stock and stall. Similar emotion was undergone by my own father when promoted for his merits from his occupation as a waterman to a situation under Government. His Christian name was Thomas. His words at the time (I was then an infant, but so deep was their impression on me, that I committed them to memory) were:

Then farewell my trim-built wherry,
Oars and coat and badge farewell!
Never more at Chelsea Ferry,
Shall your Thomas take a spell!

—My father got over it, Mr. Boffin, and so shall I.”

While delivering these valedictory observations, Wegg continually disappointed Mr. Boffin of his hand by flourishing it in the air. He now darted it at his patron, who took it, and felt his mind relieved of a great weight: observing that as they had arranged their joint affairs so satisfactorily, he would now be glad to look into those of Bully Sawyers. Which, indeed, had been left overnight in a very unpromising posture, and for whose impending expedition against the Persians the weather had been by no means favourable all day.

Mr. Wegg resumed his spectacles therefore. But Sawyers was not to be of the party that night; for, before Wegg had found his place, Mrs. Boffin’s tread was heard upon the stairs, so unusually heavy and hurried, that Mr. Boffin would have started up at the sound, anticipating some occurrence much out of the common course, even though she had not also called to him in an agitated tone.

Mr. Boffin hurried out, and found her on the dark staircase, panting, with a lighted candle in her hand.

“What’s the matter, my dear?”

“I don’t know; I don’t know; but I wish you’d come upstairs.”

Much surprised, Mr. Boffin went upstairs and accompanied Mrs. Boffin into their own room: a second large room on the same floor as the room in which the late proprietor had died. Mr. Boffin looked all round him, and saw nothing more unusual than various articles of folded linen on a large chest, which Mrs. Boffin had been sorting.

“What is it, my dear? Why, you’re frightened! You frightened?”

“I am not one of that sort certainly,” said Mrs. Boffin, as she sat down in a chair to recover herself, and took her husband’s arm; “but it’s very strange!”

“What is, my dear?”

“Noddy, the faces of the old man and the two children are all over the house tonight.”

“My dear?” exclaimed Mr. Boffin. But not without a certain uncomfortable sensation gliding down his back.

“I know it must sound foolish, and yet it is so.”

“Where did you think you saw them?”

“I don’t know that I think I saw them anywhere. I felt them.”

“Touched them?”

“No. Felt them in the air. I was sorting those things on the chest, and not thinking of the old man or the children, but singing to myself, when all in a moment I felt there was a face growing out of the dark.”

“What face?” asked her husband, looking about him.

“For a moment it was the old man’s, and then it got younger. For a moment it was both the children’s, and then it got older. For a moment it was a strange face, and then it was all the faces.”

“And then it was gone?”

“Yes; and then it was gone.”

“Where were you then, old lady?”

“Here, at the chest. Well; I got the better of it, and went on sorting, and went on singing to myself. ‘Lor!’ I says, ‘I’ll think of something else—something comfortable—and put it out of my head.’ So I thought of the new house and Miss Bella Wilfer, and was thinking at a great rate with that sheet there in my hand, when all of a sudden, the faces seemed to be hidden in among the folds of it and I let it drop.”

As it still lay on the floor where it had fallen, Mr. Boffin picked it up and laid it on the chest.

“And then you ran downstairs?”

“No. I thought I’d try another room, and shake it off. I says to myself, ‘I’ll go and walk slowly up and down the old man’s room three times, from end to end, and then I shall have conquered it.’ I went in with the candle in my hand; but the moment I came near the bed, the air got thick with them.”

“With the faces?”

“Yes, and I even felt that they were in the dark behind the side-door, and on the little staircase, floating away into the yard. Then, I called you.”

Mr. Boffin, lost in amazement, looked at Mrs. Boffin. Mrs. Boffin, lost in her own fluttered inability to make this out, looked at Mr. Boffin.

“I think, my dear,” said the Golden Dustman, “I’ll at once get rid of Wegg for the night, because he’s coming to inhabit the Bower, and it might be put into his head or somebody else’s, if he heard this and it got about that the house is haunted. Whereas we know better. Don’t we?”

“I never had the feeling in the house before,” said Mrs. Boffin; “and I have been about it alone at all hours of the night. I have been in the house when death was in it, and I have been in the house when murder was a new part of its adventures, and I never had a fright in it yet.”

“And won’t again, my dear,” said Mr. Boffin. “Depend upon it, it comes of thinking and dwelling on that dark spot.”

“Yes; but why didn’t it come before?” asked Mrs. Boffin.

This draft on Mr. Boffin’s philosophy could only be met by that gentleman with the remark that everything that is at all, must begin at some time. Then, tucking his wife’s arm under his own, that she might not be left by herself to be troubled again, he descended to release Wegg. Who, being something drowsy after his plentiful repast, and constitutionally of a shirking temperament, was well enough pleased to stump away, without doing what he had come to do, and was paid for doing.

Mr. Boffin then put on his hat, and Mrs. Boffin her shawl; and the pair, further provided with a bunch of keys and a lighted lantern, went all over the dismal house—dismal everywhere, but in their own two rooms—from cellar to cockloft. Not resting satisfied with giving that much chase to Mrs. Boffin’s fancies, they pursued them into the yard and outbuildings, and under the mounds. And setting the lantern, when all was done, at the foot of one of the mounds, they comfortably trotted to and fro for an evening walk, to the end that the murky cobwebs in Mrs. Boffin’s brain might be blown away.

“There, my dear!” said Mr. Boffin when they came in to supper. “That was the treatment, you see. Completely worked round, haven’t you?”

“Yes, deary,” said Mrs. Boffin, laying aside her shawl. “I’m not nervous any more. I’m not a bit troubled now. I’d go anywhere about the house the same as ever. But—”

“Eh!” said Mr. Boffin.

“But I’ve only to shut my eyes.”

“And what then?”

“Why then,” said Mrs. Boffin, speaking with her eyes closed, and her left hand thoughtfully touching her brow, “then, there they are! The old man’s face, and it gets younger. The two children’s faces, and they get older. A face that I don’t know. And then all the faces!”

Opening her eyes again, and seeing her husband’s face across the table, she leaned forward to give it a pat on the cheek, and sat down to supper, declaring it to be the best face in the world.

VII

In Which a Friendly Move Is Originated

The arrangement between Mr. Boffin and his literary man, Mr. Silas Wegg, so far altered with the altered habits of Mr. Boffin’s life, as that the Roman Empire usually declined in the morning and in the eminently aristocratic family mansion, rather than in the evening, as of yore, and in Boffin’s Bower. There were occasions, however, when Mr. Boffin, seeking a brief refuge from the blandishments of fashion, would present himself at the Bower after dark, to anticipate the next sallying forth of Wegg, and would there, on the old settle, pursue the downward fortunes of those enervated and corrupted masters of the world who were by this time on their last legs. If Wegg had been worse paid for his office, or better qualified to discharge it, he would have considered these visits complimentary and agreeable; but, holding the position of a handsomely-remunerated humbug, he resented them. This was quite according to rule, for the incompetent servant, by whomsoever employed, is always against his employer. Even those born governors, noble and right honourable creatures, who have been the most imbecile in high places, have uniformly shown themselves the most opposed (sometimes in belying distrust, sometimes in vapid insolence) to their employer. What is in such wise true of the public master and servant, is equally true of the private master and servant all the world over.

When Mr. Silas Wegg did at last obtain free access to “Our House,” as he had been wont to call the mansion outside which he had sat shelterless so long, and when he did at last find it in all particulars as different from his mental plans of it as according to the nature of things it well could be, that farseeing and far-reaching character, by way of asserting himself and making out a case for compensation, affected to fall into a melancholy strain of musing over the mournful past; as if the house and he had had a fall in life together.

“And this, sir,” Silas would say to his patron, sadly nodding his head and musing, “was once Our House! This, sir, is the building from which I have so often seen those great creatures, Miss Elizabeth, Master George, Aunt Jane, and Uncle Parker”—whose very names were of his own inventing—“pass and repass! And has it come to this, indeed! Ah dear me, dear me!”

So tender were his lamentations, that the kindly Mr. Boffin was quite sorry for him, and almost felt mistrustful that in buying the house he had done him an irreparable injury.

Two or three diplomatic interviews, the result of great subtlety on Mr. Wegg’s part, but assuming the mask of careless yielding to a fortuitous combination of circumstances impelling him towards Clerkenwell, had enabled him to complete his bargain with Mr. Venus.

“Bring me round to the Bower,” said Silas, when the bargain was closed, “next Saturday evening, and if a sociable glass of old Jamaikey warm should meet your views, I am not the man to begrudge it.”

“You are aware of my being poor company, sir,” replied Mr. Venus, “but be it so.”

It being so, here is Saturday evening come, and here is Mr. Venus come, and ringing at the Bower-gate.

Mr. Wegg opens the gate, descries a sort of brown paper truncheon under Mr. Venus’s arm, and remarks, in a dry tone: “Oh! I thought perhaps you might have come in a cab.”

“No, Mr. Wegg,” replies Venus. “I am not above a parcel.”

“Above a parcel! No!” says Wegg, with some dissatisfaction. But does not openly growl, “a certain sort of parcel might be above you.”

“Here is your purchase, Mr. Wegg,” says Venus, politely handing it over, “and I am glad to restore it to the source from whence it—flowed.”

“Thankee,” says Wegg. “Now this affair is concluded, I may mention to you in a friendly way that I’ve my doubts whether, if I had consulted a lawyer, you could have kept this article back from me. I only throw it out as a legal point.”

“Do you think so, Mr. Wegg? I bought you in open contract.”

“You can’t buy human flesh and blood in this country, sir; not alive, you can’t,” says Wegg, shaking his head. “Then query, bone?”

“As a legal point?” asks Venus.

“As a legal point.”

“I am not competent to speak upon that, Mr. Wegg,” says Venus, reddening and growing something louder; “but upon a point of fact I think myself competent to speak; and as a point of fact I would have seen you—will you allow me to say, further?”

“I wouldn’t say more than further, if I was you,” Mr. Wegg suggests, pacifically.

—“Before I’d have given that packet into your hand without being paid my price for it. I don’t pretend to know how the point of law may stand, but I’m thoroughly confident upon the point of fact.”

As Mr. Venus is irritable (no doubt owing to his disappointment in love), and as it is not the cue of Mr. Wegg to have him out of temper, the latter gentleman soothingly remarks, “I only put it as a little case; I only put it ha’porthetically.”

“Then I’d rather, Mr. Wegg, you put it another time, penn’orth-etically,” is Mr. Venus’s retort, “for I tell you candidly I don’t like your little cases.”

Arrived by this time in Mr. Wegg’s sitting-room, made bright on the chilly evening by gaslight and fire, Mr. Venus softens and compliments him on his abode; profiting by the occasion to remind Wegg that he (Venus) told him he had got into a good thing.

“Tolerable,” Wegg rejoins. “But bear in mind, Mr. Venus, that there’s no gold without its alloy. Mix for yourself and take a seat in the chimbley-corner. Will you perform upon a pipe, sir?”

“I am but an indifferent performer, sir,” returns the other; “but I’ll accompany you with a whiff or two at intervals.”

So, Mr. Venus mixes, and Wegg mixes; and Mr. Venus lights and puffs, and Wegg lights and puffs.

“And there’s alloy even in this metal of yours, Mr. Wegg, you was remarking?”

“Mystery,” returns Wegg. “I don’t like it, Mr. Venus. I don’t like to have the life knocked out of former inhabitants of this house, in the gloomy dark, and not know who did it.”

“Might you have any suspicions, Mr. Wegg?”

“No,” returns that gentleman. “I know who profits by it. But I’ve no suspicions.”

Having said which, Mr. Wegg smokes and looks at the fire with a most determined expression of Charity; as if he had caught that cardinal virtue by the skirts as she felt it her painful duty to depart from him, and held her by main force.

“Similarly,” resumes Wegg, “I have observations as I can offer upon certain points and parties; but I make no objections, Mr. Venus. Here is an immense fortune drops from the clouds upon a person that shall be nameless. Here is a weekly allowance, with a certain weight of coals, drops from the clouds upon me. Which of us is the better man? Not the person that shall be nameless. That’s an observation of mine, but I don’t make it an objection. I take my allowance and my certain weight of coals. He takes his fortune. That’s the way it works.”

“It would be a good thing for me, if I could see things in the calm light you do, Mr. Wegg.”

“Again look here,” pursues Silas, with an oratorical flourish of his pipe and his wooden leg: the latter having an undignified tendency to tilt him back in his chair; “here’s another observation, Mr. Venus, unaccompanied with an objection. Him that shall be nameless is liable to be talked over. He gets talked over. Him that shall be nameless, having me at his right hand, naturally looking to be promoted higher, and you may perhaps say meriting to be promoted higher—”

(Mr. Venus murmurs that he does say so.)

“—Him that shall be nameless, under such circumstances passes me by, and puts a talking-over stranger above my head. Which of us two is the better man? Which of us two can repeat most poetry? Which of us two has, in the service of him that shall be nameless, tackled the Romans, both civil and military, till he has got as husky as if he’d been weaned and ever since brought up on sawdust? Not the talking-over stranger. Yet the house is as free to him as if it was his, and he has his room, and is put upon a footing, and draws about a thousand a year. I am banished to the Bower, to be found in it like a piece of furniture whenever wanted. Merit, therefore, don’t win. That’s the way it works. I observe it, because I can’t help observing it, being accustomed to take a powerful sight of notice; but I don’t object. Ever here before, Mr. Venus?”

“Not inside the gate, Mr. Wegg.”

“You’ve been as far as the gate then, Mr. Venus?”

“Yes, Mr. Wegg, and peeped in from curiosity.”

“Did you see anything?”

“Nothing but the dust-yard.”

Mr. Wegg rolls his eyes all round the room, in that ever unsatisfied quest of his, and then rolls his eyes all round Mr. Venus; as if suspicious of his having something about him to be found out.

“And yet, sir,” he pursues, “being acquainted with old Mr. Harmon, one would have thought it might have been polite in you, too, to give him a call. And you’re naturally of a polite disposition, you are.” This last clause as a softening compliment to Mr. Venus.

“It is true, sir,” replies Venus, winking his weak eyes, and running his fingers through his dusty shock of hair, “that I was so, before a certain observation soured me. You understand to what I allude, Mr. Wegg? To a certain written statement respecting not wishing to be regarded in a certain light. Since that, all is fled, save gall.”

“Not all,” says Mr. Wegg, in a tone of sentimental condolence.

“Yes, sir,” returns Venus, “all! The world may deem it harsh, but I’d quite as soon pitch into my best friend as not. Indeed, I’d sooner!”

Involuntarily making a pass with his wooden leg to guard himself as Mr. Venus springs up in the emphasis of this unsociable declaration, Mr. Wegg tilts over on his back, chair and all, and is rescued by that harmless misanthrope, in a disjointed state and ruefully rubbing his head.

“Why, you lost your balance, Mr. Wegg,” says Venus, handing him his pipe.

“And about time to do it,” grumbles Silas, “when a man’s visitors, without a word of notice, conduct themselves with the sudden wiciousness of Jacks-in-boxes! Don’t come flying out of your chair like that, Mr. Venus!”

“I ask your pardon, Mr. Wegg. I am so soured.”

“Yes, but hang it,” says Wegg argumentatively, “a well-governed mind can be soured sitting! And as to being regarded in lights, there’s bumpy lights as well as bony. in which,” again rubbing his head, “I object to regard myself.”

“I’ll bear it in memory, sir.”

“If you’ll be so good.” Mr. Wegg slowly subdues his ironical tone and his lingering irritation, and resumes his pipe. “We were talking of old Mr. Harmon being a friend of yours.”

“Not a friend, Mr. Wegg. Only known to speak to, and to have a little deal with now and then. A very inquisitive character, Mr. Wegg, regarding what was found in the dust. As inquisitive as secret.”

“Ah! You found him secret?” returns Wegg, with a greedy relish.

“He had always the look of it, and the manner of it.”

“Ah!” with another roll of his eyes. “As to what was found in the dust now. Did you ever hear him mention how he found it, my dear friend? Living on the mysterious premises, one would like to know. For instance, where he found things? Or, for instance, how he set about it? Whether he began at the top of the mounds, or whether he began at the bottom. Whether he prodded”; Mr. Wegg’s pantomime is skilful and expressive here; “or whether he scooped? Should you say scooped, my dear Mr. Venus; or should you as a man—say prodded?”

“I should say neither, Mr. Wegg.”

“As a fellow-man, Mr. Venus—mix again—why neither?”

“Because I suppose, sir, that what was found, was found in the sorting and sifting. All the mounds are sorted and sifted?”

“You shall see ’em and pass your opinion. Mix again.”

On each occasion of his saying “mix again,” Mr. Wegg, with a hop on his wooden leg, hitches his chair a little nearer; more as if he were proposing that himself and Mr. Venus should mix again, than that they should replenish their glasses.

“Living (as I said before) on the mysterious premises,” says Wegg when the other has acted on his hospitable entreaty, “one likes to know. Would you be inclined to say now—as a brother—that he ever hid things in the dust, as well as found ’em?”

“Mr. Wegg, on the whole I should say he might.”

Mr. Wegg claps on his spectacles, and admiringly surveys Mr. Venus from head to foot.

“As a mortal equally with myself, whose hand I take in mine for the first time this day, having unaccountably overlooked that act so full of boundless confidence binding a fellow-creetur to a fellow creetur,” says Wegg, holding Mr. Venus’s palm out, flat and ready for smiting, and now smiting it; “as such—and no other—for I scorn all lowlier ties betwixt myself and the man walking with his face erect that alone I call my Twin—regarded and regarding in this trustful bond—what do you think he might have hid?”

“It is but a supposition, Mr. Wegg.”

“As a being with his hand upon his heart,” cries Wegg; and the apostrophe is not the less impressive for the being’s hand being actually upon his rum and water; “put your supposition into language, and bring it out, Mr. Venus!”

“He was the species of old gentleman, sir,” slowly returns that practical anatomist, after drinking, “that I should judge likely to take such opportunities as this place offered, of stowing away money, valuables, maybe papers.”

“As one that was ever an ornament to human life,” says Mr. Wegg, again holding out Mr. Venus’s palm as if he were going to tell his fortune by chiromancy, and holding his own up ready for smiting it when the time should come; “as one that the poet might have had his eye on, in writing the national naval words:

Helm a-weather, now lay her close,
Yard arm and yard arm she lies;
Again, cried I, Mr. Venus, give her t’other dose,
Man shrouds and grapple, sir, or she flies!

—that is to say, regarded in the light of true British Oak, for such you are—explain, Mr. Venus, the expression ‘papers’!”

“Seeing that the old gentleman was generally cutting off some near relation, or blocking out some natural affection,” Mr. Venus rejoins, “he most likely made a good many wills and codicils.”

The palm of Silas Wegg descends with a sounding smack upon the palm of Venus, and Wegg lavishly exclaims, “Twin in opinion equally with feeling! Mix a little more!”

Having now hitched his wooden leg and his chair close in front of Mr. Venus, Mr. Wegg rapidly mixes for both, gives his visitor his glass, touches its rim with the rim of his own, puts his own to his lips, puts it down, and spreading his hands on his visitor’s knees thus addresses him:

“Mr. Venus. It ain’t that I object to being passed over for a stranger, though I regard the stranger as a more than doubtful customer. It ain’t for the sake of making money, though money is ever welcome. It ain’t for myself, though I am not so haughty as to be above doing myself a good turn. It’s for the cause of the right.”

Mr. Venus, passively winking his weak eyes both at once, demands: “What is, Mr. Wegg?”

“The friendly move, sir, that I now propose. You see the move, sir?”

“Till you have pointed it out, Mr. Wegg, I can’t say whether I do or not.”

“If there is anything to be found on these premises, let us find it together. Let us make the friendly move of agreeing to look for it together. Let us make the friendly move of agreeing to share the profits of it equally betwixt us. In the cause of the right.” Thus Silas assuming a noble air.

“Then,” says Mr. Venus, looking up, after meditating with his hair held in his hands, as if he could only fix his attention by fixing his head; “if anything was to be unburied from under the dust, it would be kept a secret by you and me? Would that be it, Mr. Wegg?”

“That would depend upon what it was, Mr. Venus. Say it was money, or plate, or jewellery, it would be as much ours as anybody else’s.”

Mr. Venus rubs an eyebrow, interrogatively.

“In the cause of the right it would. Because it would be unknowingly sold with the mounds else, and the buyer would get what he was never meant to have, and never bought. And what would that be, Mr. Venus, but the cause of the wrong?”

“Say it was papers,” Mr. Venus propounds.

“According to what they contained we should offer to dispose of ’em to the parties most interested,” replies Wegg, promptly.

“In the cause of the right, Mr. Wegg?”

“Always so, Mr. Venus. If the parties should use them in the cause of the wrong, that would be their act and deed. Mr. Venus. I have an opinion of you, sir, to which it is not easy to give mouth. Since I called upon you that evening when you were, as I may say, floating your powerful mind in tea, I have felt that you required to be roused with an object. In this friendly move, sir, you will have a glorious object to rouse you.”

Mr. Wegg then goes on to enlarge upon what throughout has been uppermost in his crafty mind:—the qualifications of Mr. Venus for such a search. He expatiates on Mr. Venus’s patient habits and delicate manipulation; on his skill in piecing little things together; on his knowledge of various tissues and textures; on the likelihood of small indications leading him on to the discovery of great concealments. “While as to myself,” says Wegg, “I am not good at it. Whether I gave myself up to prodding, or whether I gave myself up to scooping, I couldn’t do it with that delicate touch so as not to show that I was disturbing the mounds. Quite different with you, going to work (as you would) in the light of a fellow-man, holily pledged in a friendly move to his brother man.” Mr. Wegg next modestly remarks on the want of adaptation in a wooden leg to ladders and suchlike airy perches, and also hints at an inherent tendency in that timber fiction, when called into action for the purposes of a promenade on an ashey slope, to stick itself into the yielding foothold, and peg its owner to one spot. Then, leaving this part of the subject, he remarks on the special phenomenon that before his installation in the Bower, it was from Mr. Venus that he first heard of the legend of hidden wealth in the Mounds: “which,” he observes with a vaguely pious air, “was surely never meant for nothing.” Lastly, he returns to the cause of the right, gloomily foreshadowing the possibility of something being unearthed to criminate Mr. Boffin (of whom he once more candidly admits it cannot be denied that he profits by a murder), and anticipating his denunciation by the friendly movers to avenging justice. And this, Mr. Wegg expressly points out, not at all for the sake of the reward—though it would be a want of principle not to take it.

To all this, Mr. Venus, with his shock of dusty hair cocked after the manner of a terrier’s ears, attends profoundly. When Mr. Wegg, having finished, opens his arms wide, as if to show Mr. Venus how bare his breast is, and then folds them pending a reply, Mr. Venus winks at him with both eyes some little time before speaking.

“I see you have tried it by yourself, Mr. Wegg,” he says when he does speak. “You have found out the difficulties by experience.”

“No, it can hardly be said that I have tried it,” replies Wegg, a little dashed by the hint. “I have just skimmed it. Skimmed it.”

“And found nothing besides the difficulties?”

Wegg shakes his head.

“I scarcely know what to say to this, Mr. Wegg,” observes Venus, after ruminating for a while.

“Say yes,” Wegg naturally urges.

“If I wasn’t soured, my answer would be No. But being soured, Mr. Wegg, and driven to reckless madness and desperation, I suppose it’s Yes.”

Wegg joyfully reproduces the two glasses, repeats the ceremony of clinking their rims, and inwardly drinks with great heartiness to the health and success in life of the young lady who has reduced Mr. Venus to his present convenient state of mind.

The articles of the friendly move are then severally recited and agreed upon. They are but secrecy, fidelity, and perseverance. The Bower to be always free of access to Mr. Venus for his researches, and every precaution to be taken against their attracting observation in the neighbourhood.

“There’s a footstep!” exclaims Venus.

“Where?” cries Wegg, starting.

“Outside. St.!”

They are in the act of ratifying the treaty of friendly move, by shaking hands upon it. They softly break off, light their pipes which have gone out, and lean back in their chairs. No doubt, a footstep. It approaches the window, and a hand taps at the glass. “Come in!” calls Wegg; meaning come round by the door. But the heavy old-fashioned sash is slowly raised, and a head slowly looks in out of the dark background of night.

“Pray is Mr. Silas Wegg here? Oh! I see him!”

The friendly movers might not have been quite at their ease, even though the visitor had entered in the usual manner. But, leaning on the breast-high window, and staring in out of the darkness, they find the visitor extremely embarrassing. Especially Mr. Venus: who removes his pipe, draws back his head, and stares at the starer, as if it were his own Hindu baby come to fetch him home.

“Good evening, Mr. Wegg. The yard gate-lock should be looked to, if you please; it don’t catch.”

“Is it Mr. Rokesmith?” falters Wegg.

“It is Mr. Rokesmith. Don’t let me disturb you. I am not coming in. I have only a message for you, which I undertook to deliver on my way home to my lodgings. I was in two minds about coming beyond the gate without ringing: not knowing but you might have a dog about.”

“I wish I had,” mutters Wegg, with his back turned as he rose from his chair. “St.! Hush! The talking-over stranger, Mr. Venus.”

“Is that anyone I know?” inquires the staring Secretary.

“No, Mr. Rokesmith. Friend of mine. Passing the evening with me.”

“Oh! I beg his pardon. Mr. Boffin wishes you to know that he does not expect you to stay at home any evening, on the chance of his coming. It has occurred to him that he may, without intending it, have been a tie upon you. In future, if he should come without notice, he will take his chance of finding you, and it will be all the same to him if he does not. I undertook to tell you on my way. That’s all.”

With that, and “Good night,” the Secretary lowers the window, and disappears. They listen, and hear his footsteps go back to the gate, and hear the gate close after him.

“And for that individual, Mr. Venus,” remarks Wegg, when he is fully gone, “I have been passed over! Let me ask you what you think of him?”

Apparently, Mr. Venus does not know what to think of him, for he makes sundry efforts to reply, without delivering himself of any other articulate utterance than that he has “a singular look.”

“A double look, you mean, sir,” rejoins Wegg, playing bitterly upon the word. “That’s his look. Any amount of singular look for me, but not a double look! That’s an underhanded mind, sir.”

“Do you say there’s something against him?” Venus asks.

“Something against him?” repeats Wegg. “Something? What would the relief be to my feelings—as a fellow-man—if I wasn’t the slave of truth, and didn’t feel myself compelled to answer, Everything!”

See into what wonderful maudlin refuges, featherless ostriches plunge their heads! It is such unspeakable moral compensation to Wegg, to be overcome by the consideration that Mr. Rokesmith has an underhanded mind!

“On this starlight night, Mr. Venus,” he remarks, when he is showing that friendly mover out across the yard, and both are something the worse for mixing again and again: “on this starlight night to think that talking-over strangers, and underhanded minds, can go walking home under the sky, as if they was all square!”

“The spectacle of those orbs,” says Mr. Venus, gazing upward with his hat tumbling off; “brings heavy on me her crushing words that she did not wish to regard herself nor yet to be regarded in that—”

“I know! I know! You needn’t repeat ’em,” says Wegg, pressing his hand. “But think how those stars steady me in the cause of the right against some that shall be nameless. It isn’t that I bear malice. But see how they glisten with old remembrances! Old remembrances of what, sir?”

Mr. Venus begins drearily replying, “Of her words, in her own handwriting, that she does not wish to regard herself, nor yet—” when Silas cuts him short with dignity.

“No, sir! Remembrances of Our House, of Master George, of Aunt Jane, of Uncle Parker, all laid waste! All offered up sacrifices to the minion of fortune and the worm of the hour!”

VI

The Golden Dustman Falls Into Worse Company

It had come to pass that Mr. Silas Wegg now rarely attended the minion of fortune and the worm of the hour, at his (the worm’s and minion’s) own house, but lay under general instructions to await him within a certain margin of hours at the Bower. Mr. Wegg took this arrangement in great dudgeon, because the appointed hours were evening hours, and those he considered precious to the progress of the friendly move. But it was quite in character, he bitterly remarked to Mr. Venus, that the upstart who had trampled on those eminent creatures, Miss Elizabeth, Master George, Aunt Jane, and Uncle Parker, should oppress his literary man.

The Roman Empire having worked out its destruction, Mr. Boffin next appeared in a cab with Rollin’s Ancient History, which valuable work being found to possess lethargic properties, broke down, at about the period when the whole of the army of Alexander the Macedonian (at that time about forty thousand strong) burst into tears simultaneously, on his being taken with a shivering fit after bathing. The Wars of the Jews, likewise languishing under Mr. Wegg’s generalship, Mr. Boffin arrived in another cab with Plutarch: whose Lives he found in the sequel extremely entertaining, though he hoped Plutarch might not expect him to believe them all. What to believe, in the course of his reading, was Mr. Boffin’s chief literary difficulty indeed; for some time he was divided in his mind between half, all, or none; at length, when he decided, as a moderate man, to compound with half, the question still remained, which half? And that stumbling-block he never got over.

One evening, when Silas Wegg had grown accustomed to the arrival of his patron in a cab, accompanied by some profane historian charged with unutterable names of incomprehensible peoples, of impossible descent, waging wars any number of years and syllables long, and carrying illimitable hosts and riches about, with the greatest ease, beyond the confines of geography—one evening the usual time passed by, and no patron appeared. After half an hour’s grace, Mr. Wegg proceeded to the outer gate, and there executed a whistle, conveying to Mr. Venus, if perchance within hearing, the tidings of his being at home and disengaged. Forth from the shelter of a neighbouring wall, Mr. Venus then emerged.

“Brother in arms,” said Mr. Wegg, in excellent spirits, “welcome!”

In return, Mr. Venus gave him a rather dry good evening.

“Walk in, brother,” said Silas, clapping him on the shoulder, “and take your seat in my chimley corner; for what says the ballad?

‘No malice to dread, sir,
And no falsehood to fear,
But truth to delight me, Mr. Venus,
And I forgot what to cheer.
Li toddle de om dee.
And something to guide,
My ain fireside, sir,
My ain fireside.’ ”

With this quotation (depending for its neatness rather on the spirit than the words), Mr. Wegg conducted his guest to his hearth.

“And you come, brother,” said Mr. Wegg, in a hospitable glow, “you come like I don’t know what—exactly like it—I shouldn’t know you from it—shedding a halo all around you.”

“What kind of halo?” asked Mr. Venus.

“ ’Ope sir,” replied Silas. “That’s your halo.”

Mr. Venus appeared doubtful on the point, and looked rather discontentedly at the fire.

“We’ll devote the evening, brother,” exclaimed Wegg, “to prosecute our friendly move. And arterwards, crushing a flowing wine-cup—which I allude to brewing rum and water—we’ll pledge one another. For what says the poet?

‘And you needn’t Mr. Venus be your black bottle,
For surely I’ll be mine,
And we’ll take a glass with a slice of lemon in it to which you’re partial,
For auld lang syne.’ ”

This flow of quotation and hospitality in Wegg indicated his observation of some little querulousness on the part of Venus.

“Why, as to the friendly move,” observed the last-named gentleman, rubbing his knees peevishly, “one of my objections to it is, that it don’t move.”

“Rome, brother,” returned Wegg: “a city which (it may not be generally known) originated in twins and a wolf; and ended in imperial marble: wasn’t built in a day.”

“Did I say it was?” asked Venus.

“No, you did not, brother. Well inquired.”

“But I do say,” proceeded Venus, “that I am taken from among my trophies of anatomy, am called upon to exchange my human warious for mere coal-ashes warious, and nothing comes of it. I think I must give up.”

“No, sir!” remonstrated Wegg, enthusiastically. “No, Sir!

‘Charge, Chester, charge,
On, Mr. Venus, on!’

Never say die, sir! A man of your mark!”

“It’s not so much saying it that I object to,” returned Mr. Venus, “as doing it. And having got to do it whether or no, I can’t afford to waste my time on groping for nothing in cinders.”

“But think how little time you have given to the move, sir, after all,” urged Wegg. “Add the evenings so occupied together, and what do they come to? And you, sir, harmonizer with myself in opinions, views, and feelings, you with the patience to fit together on wires the whole framework of society—I allude to the human skelinton—you to give in so soon!”

“I don’t like it,” returned Mr. Venus moodily, as he put his head between his knees and stuck up his dusty hair. “And there’s no encouragement to go on.”

“Not them Mounds without,” said Mr. Wegg, extending his right hand with an air of solemn reasoning, “encouragement? Not them Mounds now looking down upon us?”

“They’re too big,” grumbled Venus. “What’s a scratch here and a scrape there, a poke in this place and a dig in the other, to them. Besides; what have we found?”

“What have we found?” cried Wegg, delighted to be able to acquiesce. “Ah! There I grant you, comrade. Nothing. But on the contrary, comrade, what may we find? There you’ll grant me. Anything.”

“I don’t like it,” pettishly returned Venus as before. “I came into it without enough consideration. And besides again. Isn’t your own Mr. Boffin well acquainted with the Mounds? And wasn’t he well acquainted with the deceased and his ways? And has he ever showed any expectation of finding anything?”

At that moment wheels were heard.

“Now, I should be loth,” said Mr. Wegg, with an air of patient injury, “to think so ill of him as to suppose him capable of coming at this time of night. And yet it sounds like him.”

A ring at the yard bell.

“It is him,” said Mr. Wegg, “and he is capable of it. I am sorry, because I could have wished to keep up a little lingering fragment of respect for him.”

Here Mr. Boffin was heard lustily calling at the yard gate, “Halloa! Wegg! Halloa!”

“Keep your seat, Mr. Venus,” said Wegg. “He may not stop.” And then called out, “Halloa, sir! Halloa! I’m with you directly, sir! Half a minute, Mr. Boffin. Coming, sir, as fast as my leg will bring me!” And so with a show of much cheerful alacrity stumped out to the gate with a light, and there, through the window of a cab, descried Mr. Boffin inside, blocked up with books.

“Here! lend a hand, Wegg,” said Mr. Boffin excitedly, “I can’t get out till the way is cleared for me. This is the Annual Register, Wegg, in a cab-full of wollumes. Do you know him?”

“Know the Animal Register, sir?” returned the Impostor, who had caught the name imperfectly. “For a trifling wager, I think I could find any animal in him, blindfold, Mr. Boffin.”

“And here’s Kirby’s Wonderful Museum,” said Mr. Boffin, “and Caulfield’s Characters, and Wilson’s. Such characters, Wegg, such characters! I must have one or two of the best of ’em tonight. It’s amazing what places they used to put the guineas in, wrapped up in rags. Catch hold of that pile of wollumes, Wegg, or it’ll bulge out and burst into the mud. Is there anyone about, to help?”

“There’s a friend of mine, sir, that had the intention of spending the evening with me when I gave you up—much against my will—for the night.”

“Call him out,” cried Mr. Boffin in a bustle; “get him to bear a hand. Don’t drop that one under your arm. It’s Dancer. Him and his sister made pies of a dead sheep they found when they were out a walking. Where’s your friend? Oh, here’s your friend. Would you be so good as help Wegg and myself with these books? But don’t take Jemmy Taylor of Southwark, nor yet Jemmy Wood of Gloucester. These are the two Jemmys. I’ll carry them myself.”

Not ceasing to talk and bustle, in a state of great excitement, Mr. Boffin directed the removal and arrangement of the books, appearing to be in some sort beside himself until they were all deposited on the floor, and the cab was dismissed.

“There!” said Mr. Boffin, gloating over them. “There they are, like the four-and-twenty fiddlers—all of a row. Get on your spectacles, Wegg; I know where to find the best of ’em, and we’ll have a taste at once of what we have got before us. What’s your friend’s name?”

Mr. Wegg presented his friend as Mr. Venus.

“Eh?” cried Mr. Boffin, catching at the name. “Of Clerkenwell?”

“Of Clerkenwell, sir,” said Mr. Venus.

“Why, I’ve heard of you,” cried Mr. Boffin, “I heard of you in the old man’s time. You knew him. Did you ever buy anything of him?” With piercing eagerness.

“No, sir,” returned Venus.

“But he showed you things; didn’t he?”

Mr. Venus, with a glance at his friend, replied in the affirmative.

“What did he show you?” asked Mr. Boffin, putting his hands behind him, and eagerly advancing his head. “Did he show you boxes, little cabinets, pocketbooks, parcels, anything locked or sealed, anything tied up?”

Mr. Venus shook his head.

“Are you a judge of china?”

Mr. Venus again shook his head.

“Because if he had ever showed you a teapot, I should be glad to know of it,” said Mr. Boffin. And then, with his right hand at his lips, repeated thoughtfully, “a teapot, a teapot,” and glanced over the books on the floor, as if he knew there was something interesting connected with a teapot, somewhere among them.

Mr. Wegg and Mr. Venus looked at one another wonderingly: and Mr. Wegg, in fitting on his spectacles, opened his eyes wide, over their rims, and tapped the side of his nose: as an admonition to Venus to keep himself generally wide awake.

“A teapot,” repeated Mr. Boffin, continuing to muse and survey the books; “a teapot, a teapot. Are you ready, Wegg?”

“I am at your service, sir,” replied that gentleman, taking his usual seat on the usual settle, and poking his wooden leg under the table before it. “Mr. Venus, would you make yourself useful, and take a seat beside me, sir, for the conveniency of snuffing the candles?”

Venus complying with the invitation while it was yet being given, Silas pegged at him with his wooden leg, to call his particular attention to Mr. Boffin standing musing before the fire, in the space between the two settles.

“Hem! Ahem!” coughed Mr. Wegg to attract his employer’s attention. “Would you wish to commence with an animal, sir—from the Register?”

“No,” said Mr. Boffin, “no, Wegg.” With that, producing a little book from his breast-pocket, he handed it with great care to the literary gentlemen, and inquired, “What do you call that, Wegg?”

“This, sir,” replied Silas, adjusting his spectacles, and referring to the titlepage, “is Merryweather’s Lives and Anecdotes of Misers. Mr. Venus, would you make yourself useful and draw the candles a little nearer, sir?” This to have a special opportunity of bestowing a stare upon his comrade.

“Which of ’em have you got in that lot?” asked Mr. Boffin. “Can you find out pretty easy?”

“Well, sir,” replied Silas, turning to the table of contents and slowly fluttering the leaves of the book, “I should say they must be pretty well all here, sir; here’s a large assortment, sir; my eye catches John Overs, sir, John Little, sir, Dick Jarrel, John Elwes, the Reverend Mr. Jones of Blewbury, Vulture Hopkins, Daniel Dancer—”

“Give us Dancer, Wegg,” said Mr. Boffin.

With another stare at his comrade, Silas sought and found the place.

“Page a hundred and nine, Mr. Boffin. Chapter eight. Contents of chapter, ‘His birth and estate. His garments and outward appearance. Miss Dancer and her feminine graces. The Miser’s Mansion. The finding of a treasure. The Story of the Mutton Pies. A Miser’s Idea of Death. Bob, the Miser’s cur. Griffiths and his Master. How to turn a penny. A substitute for a Fire. The Advantages of keeping a Snuffbox. The Miser dies without a Shirt. The Treasures of a Dunghill—”

“Eh? What’s that?” demanded Mr. Boffin.

“ ‘The Treasures,’ sir,” repeated Silas, reading very distinctly, “ ‘of a Dunghill.’ Mr. Venus, sir, would you obleege with the snuffers?” This, to secure attention to his adding with his lips only, “Mounds!”

Mr. Boffin drew an armchair into the space where he stood, and said, seating himself and slyly rubbing his hands:

“Give us Dancer.”

Mr. Wegg pursued the biography of that eminent man through its various phases of avarice and dirt, through Miss Dancer’s death on a sick regimen of cold dumpling, and through Mr. Dancer’s keeping his rags together with a hayband, and warming his dinner by sitting upon it, down to the consolatory incident of his dying naked in a sack. After which he read on as follows:

“ ‘The house, or rather the heap of ruins, in which Mr. Dancer lived, and which at his death devolved to the right of Captain Holmes, was a most miserable, decayed building, for it had not been repaired for more than half a century.’ ”

(Here Mr. Wegg eyes his comrade and the room in which they sat: which had not been repaired for a long time.)

“ ‘But though poor in external structure, the ruinous fabric was very rich in the interior. It took many weeks to explore its whole contents; and Captain Holmes found it a very agreeable task to dive into the miser’s secret hoards.’ ”

(Here Mr. Wegg repeated “secret hoards,” and pegged his comrade again.)

“ ‘One of Mr. Dancer’s richest escretoires was found to be a dungheap in the cowhouse; a sum but little short of two thousand five hundred pounds was contained in this rich piece of manure; and in an old jacket, carefully tied, and strongly nailed down to the manger, in bank notes and gold were found five hundred pounds more.’ ”

(Here Mr. Wegg’s wooden leg started forward under the table, and slowly elevated itself as he read on.)

“ ‘Several bowls were discovered filled with guineas and half-guineas; and at different times on searching the corners of the house they found various parcels of bank notes. Some were crammed into the crevices of the wall’ ”;

(Here Mr. Venus looked at the wall.)

“ ‘Bundles were hid under the cushions and covers of the chairs’ ”;

(Here Mr. Venus looked under himself on the settle.)

“ ‘Some were reposing snugly at the back of the drawers; and notes amounting to six hundred pounds were found neatly doubled up in the inside of an old teapot. In the stable the Captain found jugs full of old dollars and shillings. The chimney was not left unsearched, and paid very well for the trouble; for in nineteen different holes, all filled with soot, were found various sums of money, amounting together to more than two hundred pounds.’ ”

On the way to this crisis Mr. Wegg’s wooden leg had gradually elevated itself more and more, and he had nudged Mr. Venus with his opposite elbow deeper and deeper, until at length the preservation of his balance became incompatible with the two actions, and he now dropped over sideways upon that gentleman, squeezing him against the settle’s edge. Nor did either of the two, for some few seconds, make any effort to recover himself; both remaining in a kind of pecuniary swoon.

But the sight of Mr. Boffin sitting in the armchair hugging himself, with his eyes upon the fire, acted as a restorative. Counterfeiting a sneeze to cover their movements, Mr. Wegg, with a spasmodic “Tish-ho!” pulled himself and Mr. Venus up in a masterly manner.

“Let’s have some more,” said Mr. Boffin, hungrily.

“John Elwes is the next, sir. Is it your pleasure to take John Elwes?”

“Ah!” said Mr. Boffin. “Let’s hear what John did.”

He did not appear to have hidden anything, so went off rather flatly. But an exemplary lady named Wilcocks, who had stowed away gold and silver in a pickle-pot in a clock-case, a canister-full of treasure in a hole under her stairs, and a quantity of money in an old rattrap, revived the interest. To her succeeded another lady, claiming to be a pauper, whose wealth was found wrapped up in little scraps of paper and old rag. To her, another lady, apple-woman by trade, who had saved a fortune of ten thousand pounds and hidden it “here and there, in cracks and corners, behind bricks and under the flooring.” To her, a French gentleman, who had crammed up his chimney, rather to the detriment of its drawing powers, “a leather valise, containing twenty thousand francs, gold coins, and a large quantity of precious stones,” as discovered by a chimney-sweep after his death. By these steps Mr. Wegg arrived at a concluding instance of the human Magpie:

“Many years ago, there lived at Cambridge a miserly old couple of the name of Jardine: they had two sons: the father was a perfect miser, and at his death one thousand guineas were discovered secreted in his bed. The two sons grew up as parsimonious as their sire. When about twenty years of age, they commenced business at Cambridge as drapers, and they continued there until their death. The establishment of the Messrs. Jardine was the most dirty of all the shops in Cambridge. Customers seldom went in to purchase, except perhaps out of curiosity. The brothers were most disreputable-looking beings; for, although surrounded with gay apparel as their staple in trade, they wore the most filthy rags themselves. It is said that they had no bed, and, to save the expense of one, always slept on a bundle of packing-cloths under the counter. In their housekeeping they were penurious in the extreme. A joint of meat did not grace their board for twenty years. Yet when the first of the brothers died, the other, much to his surprise, found large sums of money which had been secreted even from him.”

“There!” cried Mr. Boffin. “Even from him, you see! There was only two of ’em, and yet one of ’em hid from the other.”

Mr. Venus, who since his introduction to the French gentleman, had been stooping to peer up the chimney, had his attention recalled by the last sentence, and took the liberty of repeating it.

“Do you like it?” asked Mr. Boffin, turning suddenly.

“I beg your pardon, sir?”

“Do you like what Wegg’s been a-reading?”

Mr. Venus answered that he found it extremely interesting.

“Then come again,” said Mr. Boffin, “and hear some more. Come when you like; come the day after tomorrow, half an hour sooner. There’s plenty more; there’s no end to it.”

Mr. Venus expressed his acknowledgments and accepted the invitation.

“It’s wonderful what’s been hid, at one time and another,” said Mr. Boffin, ruminating; “truly wonderful.”

“Meaning sir,” observed Wegg, with a propitiatory face to draw him out, and with another peg at his friend and brother, “in the way of money?”

“Money,” said Mr. Boffin. “Ah! And papers.”

Mr. Wegg, in a languid transport, again dropped over on Mr. Venus, and again recovering himself, masked his emotions with a sneeze.

“Tish-ho! Did you say papers too, sir? Been hidden, sir?”

“Hidden and forgot,” said Mr. Boffin. “Why the bookseller that sold me the Wonderful Museum—where’s the Wonderful Museum?” He was on his knees on the floor in a moment, groping eagerly among the books.

“Can I assist you, sir?” asked Wegg.

“No, I have got it; here it is,” said Mr. Boffin, dusting it with the sleeve of his coat. “Wollume four. I know it was the fourth wollume, that the bookseller read it to me out of. Look for it, Wegg.”

Silas took the book and turned the leaves.

“Remarkable petrefaction, sir?”

“No, that’s not it,” said Mr. Boffin. “It can’t have been a petrefaction.”

“Memoirs of General John Reid, commonly called The Walking Rushlight, sir? With portrait?”

“No, nor yet him,” said Mr. Boffin.

“Remarkable case of a person who swallowed a crown-piece, sir?”

“To hide it?” asked Mr. Boffin.

“Why, no, sir,” replied Wegg, consulting the text, “it appears to have been done by accident. Oh! This next must be it. ‘Singular discovery of a will, lost twenty-one years.’ ”

“That’s it!” cried Mr. Boffin. “Read that.”

“ ‘A most extraordinary case,’ ” read Silas Wegg aloud, “ ‘was tried at the last Maryborough assizes in Ireland. It was briefly this. Robert Baldwin, in March 1782, made his will, in which he devised the lands now in question, to the children of his youngest son; soon after which his faculties failed him, and he became altogether childish and died, above eighty years old. The defendant, the eldest son, immediately afterwards gave out that his father had destroyed the will; and no will being found, he entered into possession of the lands in question, and so matters remained for twenty-one years, the whole family during all that time believing that the father had died without a will. But after twenty-one years the defendant’s wife died, and he very soon afterwards, at the age of seventy-eight, married a very young woman: which caused some anxiety to his two sons, whose poignant expressions of this feeling so exasperated their father, that he in his resentment executed a will to disinherit his eldest son, and in his fit of anger showed it to his second son, who instantly determined to get at it, and destroy it, in order to preserve the property to his brother. With this view, he broke open his father’s desk, where he found—not his father’s will which he sought after, but the will of his grandfather, which was then altogether forgotten in the family.’ ”

“There!” said Mr. Boffin. “See what men put away and forget, or mean to destroy, and don’t!” He then added in a slow tone, “As—ton—ish—ing!” And as he rolled his eyes all round the room, Wegg and Venus likewise rolled their eyes all round the room. And then Wegg, singly, fixed his eyes on Mr. Boffin looking at the fire again; as if he had a mind to spring upon him and demand his thoughts or his life.

“However, time’s up for tonight,” said Mr. Boffin, waving his hand after a silence. “More, the day after tomorrow. Range the books upon the shelves, Wegg. I dare say Mr. Venus will be so kind as help you.”

While speaking, he thrust his hand into the breast of his outer coat, and struggled with some object there that was too large to be got out easily. What was the stupefaction of the friendly movers when this object at last emerging, proved to be a much-dilapidated dark lantern!

Without at all noticing the effect produced by this little instrument, Mr. Boffin stood it on his knee, and, producing a box of matches, deliberately lighted the candle in the lantern, blew out the kindled match, and cast the end into the fire. “I’m going, Wegg,” he then announced, “to take a turn about the place and round the yard. I don’t want you. Me and this same lantern have taken hundreds—thousands—of such turns in our time together.”

“But I couldn’t think, sir—not on any account, I couldn’t,”—Wegg was politely beginning, when Mr. Boffin, who had risen and was going towards the door, stopped:

“I have told you that I don’t want you, Wegg.”

Wegg looked intelligently thoughtful, as if that had not occurred to his mind until he now brought it to bear on the circumstance. He had nothing for it but to let Mr. Boffin go out and shut the door behind him. But, the instant he was on the other side of it, Wegg clutched Venus with both hands, and said in a choking whisper, as if he were being strangled:

“Mr. Venus, he must be followed, he must be watched, he mustn’t be lost sight of for a moment.”

“Why mustn’t he?” asked Venus, also strangling.

“Comrade, you might have noticed I was a little elewated in spirits when you come in tonight. I’ve found something.”

“What have you found?” asked Venus, clutching him with both hands, so that they stood interlocked like a couple of preposterous gladiators.

“There’s no time to tell you now. I think he must have gone to look for it. We must have an eye upon him instantly.”

Releasing each other, they crept to the door, opened it softly, and peeped out. It was a cloudy night, and the black shadow of the Mounds made the dark yard darker. “If not a double swindler,” whispered Wegg, “why a dark lantern? We could have seen what he was about, if he had carried a light one. Softly, this way.”

Cautiously along the path that was bordered by fragments of crockery set in ashes, the two stole after him. They could hear him at his peculiar trot, crushing the loose cinders as he went. “He knows the place by heart,” muttered Silas, “and don’t need to turn his lantern on, confound him!” But he did turn it on, almost in that same instant, and flashed its light upon the first of the Mounds.

“Is that the spot?” asked Venus in a whisper.

“He’s warm,” said Silas in the same tone. “He’s precious warm. He’s close. I think he must be going to look for it. What’s that he’s got in his hand?”

“A shovel,” answered Venus. “And he knows how to use it, remember, fifty times as well as either of us.”

“If he looks for it and misses it, partner,” suggested Wegg, “what shall we do?”

“First of all, wait till he does,” said Venus.

Discreet advice too, for he darkened his lantern again, and the mound turned black. After a few seconds, he turned the light on once more, and was seen standing at the foot of the second mound, slowly raising the lantern little by little until he held it up at arm’s length, as if he were examining the condition of the whole surface.

“That can’t be the spot too?” said Venus.

“No,” said Wegg, “he’s getting cold.”

“It strikes me,” whispered Venus, “that he wants to find out whether anyone has been groping about there.”

“Hush!” returned Wegg, “he’s getting colder and colder.—Now he’s freezing!”

This exclamation was elicited by his having turned the lantern off again, and on again, and being visible at the foot of the third mound.

“Why, he’s going up it!” said Venus.

“Shovel and all!” said Wegg.

At a nimbler trot, as if the shovel over his shoulder stimulated him by reviving old associations, Mr. Boffin ascended the “serpentining walk,” up the Mound which he had described to Silas Wegg on the occasion of their beginning to decline and fall. On striking into it he turned his lantern off. The two followed him, stooping low, so that their figures might make no mark in relief against the sky when he should turn his lantern on again. Mr. Venus took the lead, towing Mr. Wegg, in order that his refractory leg might be promptly extricated from any pitfalls it should dig for itself. They could just make out that the Golden Dustman stopped to breathe. Of course they stopped too, instantly.

“This is his own Mound,” whispered Wegg, as he recovered his wind, “this one.”

“Why all three are his own,” returned Venus.

“So he thinks; but he’s used to call this his own, because it’s the one first left to him; the one that was his legacy when it was all he took under the will.”

“When he shows his light,” said Venus, keeping watch upon his dusky figure all the time, “drop lower and keep closer.”

He went on again, and they followed again. Gaining the top of the Mound, he turned on his light—but only partially—and stood it on the ground. A bare lopsided weatherbeaten pole was planted in the ashes there, and had been there many a year. Hard by this pole, his lantern stood: lighting a few feet of the lower part of it and a little of the ashy surface around, and then casting off a purposeless little clear trail of light into the air.

“He can never be going to dig up the pole!” whispered Venus as they dropped low and kept close.

“Perhaps it’s holler and full of something,” whispered Wegg.

He was going to dig, with whatsoever object, for he tucked up his cuffs and spat on his hands, and then went at it like an old digger as he was. He had no design upon the pole, except that he measured a shovel’s length from it before beginning, nor was it his purpose to dig deep. Some dozen or so of expert strokes sufficed. Then, he stopped, looked down into the cavity, bent over it, and took out what appeared to be an ordinary case-bottle: one of those squat, high-shouldered, short-necked glass bottles which the Dutchman is said to keep his courage in. As soon as he had done this, he turned off his lantern, and they could hear that he was filling up the hole in the dark. The ashes being easily moved by a skilful hand, the spies took this as a hint to make off in good time. Accordingly, Mr. Venus slipped past Mr. Wegg and towed him down. But Mr. Wegg’s descent was not accomplished without some personal inconvenience, for his self-willed leg sticking into the ashes about halfway down, and time pressing, Mr. Venus took the liberty of hauling him from his tether by the collar: which occasioned him to make the rest of the journey on his back, with his head enveloped in the skirts of his coat, and his wooden leg coming last, like a drag. So flustered was Mr. Wegg by this mode of travelling, that when he was set on the level ground with his intellectual developments uppermost, he was quite unconscious of his bearings, and had not the least idea where his place of residence was to be found, until Mr. Venus shoved him into it. Even then he staggered round and round, weakly staring about him, until Mr. Venus with a hard brush brushed his senses into him and the dust out of him.

Mr. Boffin came down leisurely, for this brushing process had been well accomplished, and Mr. Venus had had time to take his breath, before he reappeared. That he had the bottle somewhere about him could not be doubted; where, was not so clear. He wore a large rough coat, buttoned over, and it might be in any one of half a dozen pockets.

“What’s the matter, Wegg?” said Mr. Boffin. “You are as pale as a candle.”

Mr. Wegg replied, with literal exactness, that he felt as if he had had a turn.

“Bile,” said Mr. Boffin, blowing out the light in the lantern, shutting it up, and stowing it away in the breast of his coat as before. “Are you subject to bile, Wegg?”

Mr. Wegg again replied, with strict adherence to truth, that he didn’t think he had ever had a similar sensation in his head, to anything like the same extent.

“Physic yourself tomorrow, Wegg,” said Mr. Boffin, “to be in order for next night. By the by, this neighbourhood is going to have a loss, Wegg.”

“A loss, sir?”

“Going to lose the Mounds.”

The friendly movers made such an obvious effort not to look at one another, that they might as well have stared at one another with all their might.

“Have you parted with them, Mr. Boffin?” asked Silas.

“Yes; they’re going. Mine’s as good as gone already.”

“You mean the little one of the three, with the pole atop, sir.”

“Yes,” said Mr. Boffin, rubbing his ear in his old way, with that new touch of craftiness added to it. “It has fetched a penny. It’ll begin to be carted off tomorrow.”

“Have you been out to take leave of your old friend, sir?” asked Silas, jocosely.

“No,” said Mr. Boffin. “What the devil put that in your head?”

He was so sudden and rough, that Wegg, who had been hovering closer and closer to his skirts, despatching the back of his hand on exploring expeditions in search of the bottle’s surface, retired two or three paces.

“No offence, sir,” said Wegg, humbly. “No offence.”

Mr. Boffin eyed him as a dog might eye another dog who wanted his bone; and actually retorted with a low growl, as the dog might have retorted.

“Good night,” he said, after having sunk into a moody silence, with his hands clasped behind him, and his eyes suspiciously wandering about Wegg.—“No! stop there. I know the way out, and I want no light.”

Avarice, and the evening’s legends of avarice, and the inflammatory effect of what he had seen, and perhaps the rush of his ill-conditioned blood to his brain in his descent, wrought Silas Wegg to such a pitch of insatiable appetite, that when the door closed he made a swoop at it and drew Venus along with him.

“He mustn’t go,” he cried. “We mustn’t let him go? He has got that bottle about him. We must have that bottle.”

“Why, you wouldn’t take it by force?” said Venus, restraining him.

“Wouldn’t I? Yes I would. I’d take it by any force, I’d have it at any price! Are you so afraid of one old man as to let him go, you coward?”

“I am so afraid of you, as not to let you go,” muttered Venus, sturdily, clasping him in his arms.

“Did you hear him?” retorted Wegg. “Did you hear him say that he was resolved to disappoint us? Did you hear him say, you cur, that he was going to have the Mounds cleared off, when no doubt the whole place will be rummaged? If you haven’t the spirit of a mouse to defend your rights, I have. Let me go after him.”

As in his wildness he was making a strong struggle for it, Mr. Venus deemed it expedient to lift him, throw him, and fall with him; well knowing that, once down, he would not be up again easily with his wooden leg. So they both rolled on the floor, and, as they did so, Mr. Boffin shut the gate.

XIV

Mr. Wegg Prepares a Grindstone for Mr. Boffin’s Nose

Having assisted at a few more expositions of the lives of misers, Mr. Venus became almost indispensable to the evenings at the Bower. The circumstance of having another listener to the wonders unfolded by Wegg, or, as it were, another calculator to cast up the guineas found in teapots, chimneys, racks and mangers, and other such banks of deposit, seemed greatly to heighten Mr. Boffin’s enjoyment; while Silas Wegg, for his part, though of a jealous temperament which might under ordinary circumstances have resented the anatomist’s getting into favour, was so very anxious to keep his eye on that gentleman—lest, being too much left to himself, he should be tempted to play any tricks with the precious document in his keeping—that he never lost an opportunity of commending him to Mr. Boffin’s notice as a third party whose company was much to be desired. Another friendly demonstration towards him Mr. Wegg now regularly gratified. After each sitting was over, and the patron had departed, Mr. Wegg invariably saw Mr. Venus home. To be sure, he as invariably requested to be refreshed with a sight of the paper in which he was a joint proprietor; but he never failed to remark that it was the great pleasure he derived from Mr. Venus’s improving society which had insensibly lured him round to Clerkenwell again, and that, finding himself once more attracted to the spot by the social powers of Mr. V., he would beg leave to go through that little incidental procedure, as a matter of form. “For well I know, sir,” Mr. Wegg would add, “that a man of your delicate mind would wish to be checked off whenever the opportunity arises, and it is not for me to baulk your feelings.”

A certain rustiness in Mr. Venus, which never became so lubricated by the oil of Mr. Wegg but that he turned under the screw in a creaking and stiff manner, was very noticeable at about this period. While assisting at the literary evenings, he even went so far, on two or three occasions, as to correct Mr. Wegg when he grossly mispronounced a word, or made nonsense of a passage; insomuch that Mr. Wegg took to surveying his course in the day, and to making arrangements for getting round rocks at night instead of running straight upon them. Of the slightest anatomical reference he became particularly shy, and, if he saw a bone ahead, would go any distance out of his way rather than mention it by name.

The adverse destinies ordained that one evening Mr. Wegg’s labouring bark became beset by polysyllables, and embarrassed among a perfect archipelago of hard words. It being necessary to take soundings every minute, and to feel the way with the greatest caution, Mr. Wegg’s attention was fully employed. Advantage was taken of this dilemma by Mr. Venus, to pass a scrap of paper into Mr. Boffin’s hand, and lay his finger on his own lip.

When Mr. Boffin got home at night he found that the paper contained Mr. Venus’s card and these words: “Should be glad to be honoured with a call respecting business of your own, about dusk on an early evening.”

The very next evening saw Mr. Boffin peeping in at the preserved frogs in Mr. Venus’s shopwindow, and saw Mr. Venus espying Mr. Boffin with the readiness of one on the alert, and beckoning that gentleman into his interior. Responding, Mr. Boffin was invited to seat himself on the box of human miscellanies before the fire, and did so, looking round the place with admiring eyes. The fire being low and fitful, and the dusk gloomy, the whole stock seemed to be winking and blinking with both eyes, as Mr. Venus did. The French gentleman, though he had no eyes, was not at all behindhand, but appeared, as the flame rose and fell, to open and shut his no eyes, with the regularity of the glass-eyed dogs and ducks and birds. The big-headed babies were equally obliging in lending their grotesque aid to the general effect.

“You see, Mr. Venus, I’ve lost no time,” said Mr. Boffin. “Here I am.”

“Here you are, sir,” assented Mr. Venus.

“I don’t like secrecy,” pursued Mr. Boffin—“at least, not in a general way I don’t—but I dare say you’ll show me good reason for being secret so far.”

“I think I shall, sir,” returned Venus.

“Good,” said Mr. Boffin. “You don’t expect Wegg, I take it for granted?”

“No, sir. I expect no one but the present company.”

Mr. Boffin glanced about him, as accepting under that inclusive denomination the French gentleman and the circle in which he didn’t move, and repeated, “The present company.”

“Sir,” said Mr. Venus, “before entering upon business, I shall have to ask you for your word and honour that we are in confidence.”

“Let’s wait a bit and understand what the expression means,” answered Mr. Boffin. “In confidence for how long? In confidence forever and a day?”

“I take your hint, sir,” said Venus; “you think you might consider the business, when you came to know it, to be of a nature incompatible with confidence on your part?”

“I might,” said Mr. Boffin with a cautious look.

“True, sir. Well, sir,” observed Venus, after clutching at his dusty hair, to brighten his ideas, “let us put it another way. I open the business with you, relying upon your honour not to do anything in it, and not to mention me in it, without my knowledge.”

“That sounds fair,” said Mr. Boffin. “I agree to that.”

“I have your word and honour, sir?”

“My good fellow,” retorted Mr. Boffin, “you have my word; and how you can have that, without my honour too, I don’t know. I’ve sorted a lot of dust in my time, but I never knew the two things go into separate heaps.”

This remark seemed rather to abash Mr. Venus. He hesitated, and said, “Very true, sir;” and again, “Very true, sir,” before resuming the thread of his discourse.

“Mr. Boffin, if I confess to you that I fell into a proposal of which you were the subject, and of which you oughtn’t to have been the subject, you will allow me to mention, and will please take into favourable consideration, that I was in a crushed state of mind at the time.”

The Golden Dustman, with his hands folded on the top of his stout stick, with his chin resting upon them, and with something leering and whimsical in his eyes, gave a nod, and said, “Quite so, Venus.”

“That proposal, sir, was a conspiring breach of your confidence, to such an extent, that I ought at once to have made it known to you. But I didn’t, Mr. Boffin, and I fell into it.”

Without moving eye or finger, Mr. Boffin gave another nod, and placidly repeated, “Quite so, Venus.”

“Not that I was ever hearty in it, sir,” the penitent anatomist went on, “or that I ever viewed myself with anything but reproach for having turned out of the paths of science into the paths of—” he was going to say “villany,” but, unwilling to press too hard upon himself, substituted with great emphasis—“Weggery.”

Placid and whimsical of look as ever, Mr. Boffin answered:

“Quite so, Venus.”

“And now, sir,” said Venus, “having prepared your mind in the rough, I will articulate the details.” With which brief professional exordium, he entered on the history of the friendly move, and truly recounted it. One might have thought that it would have extracted some show of surprise or anger, or other emotion, from Mr. Boffin, but it extracted nothing beyond his former comment:

“Quite so, Venus.”

“I have astonished you, sir, I believe?” said Mr. Venus, pausing dubiously.

Mr. Boffin simply answered as aforesaid: “Quite so, Venus.”

By this time the astonishment was all on the other side. It did not, however, so continue. For, when Venus passed to Wegg’s discovery, and from that to their having both seen Mr. Boffin dig up the Dutch bottle, that gentleman changed colour, changed his attitude, became extremely restless, and ended (when Venus ended) by being in a state of manifest anxiety, trepidation, and confusion.

“Now, sir,” said Venus, finishing off; “you best know what was in that Dutch bottle, and why you dug it up, and took it away. I don’t pretend to know anything more about it than I saw. All I know is this: I am proud of my calling after all (though it has been attended by one dreadful drawback which has told upon my heart, and almost equally upon my skeleton), and I mean to live by my calling. Putting the same meaning into other words, I do not mean to turn a single dishonest penny by this affair. As the best amends I can make you for having ever gone into it, I make known to you, as a warning, what Wegg has found out. My opinion is, that Wegg is not to be silenced at a modest price, and I build that opinion on his beginning to dispose of your property the moment he knew his power. Whether it’s worth your while to silence him at any price, you will decide for yourself, and take your measures accordingly. As far as I am concerned, I have no price. If I am ever called upon for the truth, I tell it, but I want to do no more than I have now done and ended.”

“Thank’ee, Venus!” said Mr. Boffin, with a hearty grip of his hand; “thank’ee, Venus, thank’ee, Venus!” And then walked up and down the little shop in great agitation. “But look here, Venus,” he by-and-by resumed, nervously sitting down again; “if I have to buy Wegg up, I shan’t buy him any cheaper for your being out of it. Instead of his having half the money—it was to have been half, I suppose? Share and share alike?”

“It was to have been half, sir,” answered Venus.

“Instead of that, he’ll now have all. I shall pay the same, if not more. For you tell me he’s an unconscionable dog, a ravenous rascal.”

“He is,” said Venus.

“Don’t you think, Venus,” insinuated Mr. Boffin, after looking at the fire for a while—“don’t you feel as if—you might like to pretend to be in it till Wegg was bought up, and then ease your mind by handing over to me what you had made believe to pocket?”

“No I don’t, sir,” returned Venus, very positively.

“Not to make amends?” insinuated Mr. Boffin.

“No, sir. It seems to me, after maturely thinking it over, that the best amends for having got out of the square is to get back into the square.”

“Humph!” mused Mr. Boffin. “When you say the square, you mean—”

“I mean,” said Venus, stoutly and shortly, “the right.”

“It appears to me,” said Mr. Boffin, grumbling over the fire in an injured manner, “that the right is with me, if it’s anywhere. I have much more right to the old man’s money than the Crown can ever have. What was the Crown to him except the King’s Taxes? Whereas, me and my wife, we was all in all to him.”

Mr. Venus, with his head upon his hands, rendered melancholy by the contemplation of Mr. Boffin’s avarice, only murmured to steep himself in the luxury of that frame of mind: “She did not wish so to regard herself, nor yet to be so regarded.”

“And how am I to live,” asked Mr. Boffin, piteously, “if I’m to be going buying fellows up out of the little that I’ve got? And how am I to set about it? When am I to get my money ready? When am I to make a bid? You haven’t told me when he threatens to drop down upon me.”

Venus explained under what conditions, and with what views, the dropping down upon Mr. Boffin was held over until the Mounds should be cleared away. Mr. Boffin listened attentively. “I suppose,” said he, with a gleam of hope, “there’s no doubt about the genuineness and date of this confounded will?”

“None whatever,” said Mr. Venus.

“Where might it be deposited at present?” asked Mr. Boffin, in a wheedling tone.

“It’s in my possession, sir.”

“Is it?” he cried, with great eagerness. “Now, for any liberal sum of money that could be agreed upon, Venus, would you put it in the fire?”

“No, sir, I wouldn’t,” interrupted Mr. Venus.

“Nor pass it over to me?”

“That would be the same thing. No, sir,” said Mr. Venus.

The Golden Dustman seemed about to pursue these questions, when a stumping noise was heard outside, coming towards the door. “Hush! here’s Wegg!” said Venus. “Get behind the young alligator in the corner, Mr. Boffin, and judge him for yourself. I won’t light a candle till he’s gone; there’ll only be the glow of the fire; Wegg’s well acquainted with the alligator, and he won’t take particular notice of him. Draw your legs in, Mr. Boffin, at present I see a pair of shoes at the end of his tail. Get your head well behind his smile, Mr. Boffin, and you’ll lie comfortable there; you’ll find plenty of room behind his smile. He’s a little dusty, but he’s very like you in tone. Are you right, sir?”

Mr. Boffin had but whispered an affirmative response, when Wegg came stumping in. “Partner,” said that gentleman in a sprightly manner, “how’s yourself?”

“Tolerable,” returned Mr. Venus. “Not much to boast of.”

“In‑deed!” said Wegg: “sorry, partner, that you’re not picking up faster, but your soul’s too large for your body, sir; that’s where it is. And how’s our stock in trade, partner? Safe bind, safe find, partner? Is that about it?”

“Do you wish to see it?” asked Venus.

“If you please, partner,” said Wegg, rubbing his hands. “I wish to see it jintly with yourself. Or, in similar words to some that was set to music some time back:

‘I wish you to see it with your eyes,
And I will pledge with mine.’ ”

Turning his back and turning a key, Mr. Venus produced the document, holding on by his usual corner. Mr. Wegg, holding on by the opposite corner, sat down on the seat so lately vacated by Mr. Boffin, and looked it over. “All right, sir,” he slowly and unwillingly admitted, in his reluctance to loose his hold, “all right!” And greedily watched his partner as he turned his back again, and turned his key again.

“There’s nothing new, I suppose?” said Venus, resuming his low chair behind the counter.

“Yes there is, sir,” replied Wegg; “there was something new this morning. That foxey old grasper and griper—”

“Mr. Boffin?” inquired Venus, with a glance towards the alligator’s yard or two of smile.

“Mister be blowed!” cried Wegg, yielding to his honest indignation. “Boffin. Dusty Boffin. That foxey old grunter and grinder, sir, turns into the yard this morning, to meddle with our property, a menial tool of his own, a young man by the name of Sloppy. Ecod, when I say to him, ‘What do you want here, young man? This is a private yard,’ he pulls out a paper from Boffin’s other blackguard, the one I was passed over for. ‘This is to authorize Sloppy to overlook the carting and to watch the work.’ That’s pretty strong, I think, Mr. Venus?”

“Remember he doesn’t know yet of our claim on the property,” suggested Venus.

“Then he must have a hint of it,” said Wegg, “and a strong one that’ll jog his terrors a bit. Give him an inch, and he’ll take an ell. Let him alone this time, and what’ll he do with our property next? I tell you what, Mr. Venus; it comes to this; I must be overbearing with Boffin, or I shall fly into several pieces. I can’t contain myself when I look at him. Every time I see him putting his hand in his pocket, I see him putting it into my pocket. Every time I hear him jingling his money, I hear him taking liberties with my money. Flesh and blood can’t bear it. No,” said Mr. Wegg, greatly exasperated, “and I’ll go further. A wooden leg can’t bear it!”

“But, Mr. Wegg,” urged Venus, “it was your own idea that he should not be exploded upon, till the Mounds were carted away.”

“But it was likewise my idea, Mr. Venus,” retorted Wegg, “that if he came sneaking and sniffing about the property, he should be threatened, given to understand that he has no right to it, and be made our slave. Wasn’t that my idea, Mr. Venus?”

“It certainly was, Mr. Wegg.”

“It certainly was, as you say, partner,” assented Wegg, put into a better humour by the ready admission. “Very well. I consider his planting one of his menial tools in the yard, an act of sneaking and sniffing. And his nose shall be put to the grindstone for it.”

“It was not your fault, Mr. Wegg, I must admit,” said Venus, “that he got off with the Dutch bottle that night.”

“As you handsomely say again, partner! No, it was not my fault. I’d have had that bottle out of him. Was it to be borne that he should come, like a thief in the dark, digging among stuff that was far more ours than his (seeing that we could deprive him of every grain of it, if he didn’t buy us at our own figure), and carrying off treasure from its bowels? No, it was not to be borne. And for that, too, his nose shall be put to the grindstone.”

“How do you propose to do it, Mr. Wegg?”

“To put his nose to the grindstone? I propose,” returned that estimable man, “to insult him openly. And, if looking into this eye of mine, he dares to offer a word in answer, to retort upon him before he can take his breath, ‘Add another word to that, you dusty old dog, and you’re a beggar.’ ”

“Suppose he says nothing, Mr. Wegg?”

“Then,” replied Wegg, “we shall have come to an understanding with very little trouble, and I’ll break him and drive him, Mr. Venus. I’ll put him in harness, and I’ll bear him up tight, and I’ll break him and drive him. The harder the old Dust is driven, sir, the higher he’ll pay. And I mean to be paid high, Mr. Venus, I promise you.”

“You speak quite revengefully, Mr. Wegg.”

“Revengefully, sir? Is it for him that I have declined and falled, night after night? Is it for his pleasure that I’ve waited at home of an evening, like a set of skittles, to be set up and knocked over, set up and knocked over, by whatever balls—or books—he chose to bring against me? Why, I’m a hundred times the man he is, sir; five hundred times!”

Perhaps it was with the malicious intent of urging him on to his worst that Mr. Venus looked as if he doubted that.

“What? Was it outside the house at present ockypied, to its disgrace, by that minion of fortune and worm of the hour,” said Wegg, falling back upon his strongest terms of reprobation, and slapping the counter, “that I, Silas Wegg, five hundred times the man he ever was, sat in all weathers, waiting for a errand or a customer? Was it outside that very house as I first set eyes upon him, rolling in the lap of luxury, when I was selling halfpenny ballads there for a living? And am I to grovel in the dust for him to walk over? No!”

There was a grin upon the ghastly countenance of the French gentleman under the influence of the firelight, as if he were computing how many thousand slanderers and traitors array themselves against the fortunate, on premises exactly answering to those of Mr. Wegg. One might have fancied that the big-headed babies were toppling over with their hydrocephalic attempts to reckon up the children of men who transform their benefactors into their injurers by the same process. The yard or two of smile on the part of the alligator might have been invested with the meaning, “All about this was quite familiar knowledge down in the depths of the slime, ages ago.”

“But,” said Wegg, possibly with some slight perception to the foregoing effect, “your speaking countenance remarks, Mr. Venus, that I’m duller and savager than usual. Perhaps I have allowed myself to brood too much. Begone, dull care! ’Tis gone, sir. I’ve looked in upon you, and empire resumes her sway. For, as the song says—subject to your correction, sir—

‘When the heart of a man is depressed with cares,
The mist is dispelled if Venus appears.
Like the notes of a fiddle, you sweetly, sir, sweetly,
Raises our spirits and charms our ears.’

Good night, sir.”

“I shall have a word or two to say to you, Mr. Wegg, before long,” remarked Venus, “respecting my share in the project we’ve been speaking of.”

“My time, sir,” returned Wegg, “is yours. In the meanwhile let it be fully understood that I shall not neglect bringing the grindstone to bear, nor yet bringing Dusty Boffin’s nose to it. His nose once brought to it, shall be held to it by these hands, Mr. Venus, till the sparks flies out in showers.”

With this agreeable promise Wegg stumped out, and shut the shop-door after him. “Wait till I light a candle, Mr. Boffin,” said Venus, “and you’ll come out more comfortable.” So, he lighting a candle and holding it up at arm’s length, Mr. Boffin disengaged himself from behind the alligator’s smile, with an expression of countenance so very downcast that it not only appeared as if the alligator had the whole of the joke to himself, but further as if it had been conceived and executed at Mr. Boffin’s expense.

“That’s a treacherous fellow,” said Mr. Boffin, dusting his arms and legs as he came forth, the alligator having been but musty company. “That’s a dreadful fellow.”

“The alligator, sir?” said Venus.

“No, Venus, no. The Serpent.”

“You’ll have the goodness to notice, Mr. Boffin,” remarked Venus, “that I said nothing to him about my going out of the affair altogether, because I didn’t wish to take you anyways by surprise. But I can’t be too soon out of it for my satisfaction, Mr. Boffin, and I now put it to you when it will suit your views for me to retire?”

“Thank’ee, Venus, thank’ee, Venus; but I don’t know what to say,” returned Mr. Boffin, “I don’t know what to do. He’ll drop down on me anyway. He seems fully determined to drop down; don’t he?”

Mr. Venus opined that such was clearly his intention.

“You might be a sort of protection for me, if you remained in it,” said Mr. Boffin; “you might stand betwixt him and me, and take the edge off him. Don’t you feel as if you could make a show of remaining in it, Venus, till I had time to turn myself round?”

Venus naturally inquired how long Mr. Boffin thought it might take him to turn himself round?

“I am sure I don’t know,” was the answer, given quite at a loss. “Everything is so at sixes and sevens. If I had never come into the property, I shouldn’t have minded. But being in it, it would be very trying to be turned out; now, don’t you acknowledge that it would, Venus?”

Mr. Venus preferred, he said, to leave Mr. Boffin to arrive at his own conclusions on that delicate question.

“I am sure I don’t know what to do,” said Mr. Boffin. “If I ask advice of anyone else, it’s only letting in another person to be bought out, and then I shall be ruined that way, and might as well have given up the property and gone slap to the workhouse. If I was to take advice of my young man, Rokesmith, I should have to buy him out. Sooner or later, of course, he’d drop down upon me, like Wegg. I was brought into the world to be dropped down upon, it appears to me.”

Mr. Venus listened to these lamentations in silence, while Mr. Boffin jogged to and fro, holding his pockets as if he had a pain in them.

“After all, you haven’t said what you mean to do yourself, Venus. When you do go out of it, how do you mean to go?”

Venus replied that as Wegg had found the document and handed it to him, it was his intention to hand it back to Wegg, with the declaration that he himself would have nothing to say to it, or do with it, and that Wegg must act as he chose, and take the consequences.

“And then he drops down with his whole weight upon me!” cried Mr. Boffin, ruefully. “I’d sooner be dropped upon by you than by him, or even by you jintly, than by him alone!”

Mr. Venus could only repeat that it was his fixed intention to betake himself to the paths of science, and to walk in the same all the days of his life; not dropping down upon his fellow-creatures until they were deceased, and then only to articulate them to the best of his humble ability.

“How long could you be persuaded to keep up the appearance of remaining in it?” asked Mr. Boffin, retiring on his other idea. “Could you be got to do so, till the Mounds are gone?”

No. That would protract the mental uneasiness of Mr. Venus too long, he said.

“Not if I was to show you reason now?” demanded Mr. Boffin; “not if I was to show you good and sufficient reason?”

If by good and sufficient reason Mr. Boffin meant honest and unimpeachable reason, that might weigh with Mr. Venus against his personal wishes and convenience. But he must add that he saw no opening to the possibility of such reason being shown him.

“Come and see me, Venus,” said Mr. Boffin, “at my house.”

“Is the reason there, sir?” asked Mr. Venus, with an incredulous smile and blink.

“It may be, or may not be,” said Mr. Boffin, “just as you view it. But in the meantime don’t go out of the matter. Look here. Do this. Give me your word that you won’t take any steps with Wegg, without my knowledge, just as I have given you my word that I won’t without yours.”

“Done, Mr. Boffin!” said Venus, after brief consideration.

“Thank’ee, Venus, thank’ee, Venus! Done!”

“When shall I come to see you, Mr. Boffin.”

“When you like. The sooner the better. I must be going now. Good night, Venus.”

“Good night, sir.”

“And good night to the rest of the present company,” said Mr. Boffin, glancing round the shop. “They make a queer show, Venus, and I should like to be better acquainted with them some day. Good night, Venus, good night! Thankee, Venus, thankee, Venus!” With that he jogged out into the street, and jogged upon his homeward way.

“Now, I wonder,” he meditated as he went along, nursing his stick, “whether it can be, that Venus is setting himself to get the better of Wegg? Whether it can be, that he means, when I have bought Wegg out, to have me all to himself and to pick me clean to the bones!”

It was a cunning and suspicious idea, quite in the way of his school of misers, and he looked very cunning and suspicious as he went jogging through the streets. More than once or twice, more than twice or thrice, say half a dozen times, he took his stick from the arm on which he nursed it, and hit a straight sharp rap at the air with its head. Possibly the wooden countenance of Mr. Silas Wegg was incorporeally before him at those moments, for he hit with intense satisfaction.

He was within a few streets of his own house, when a little private carriage, coming in the contrary direction, passed him, turned round, and passed him again. It was a little carriage of eccentric movement, for again he heard it stop behind him and turn round, and again he saw it pass him. Then it stopped, and then went on, out of sight. But, not far out of sight, for, when he came to the corner of his own street, there it stood again.

There was a lady’s face at the window as he came up with this carriage, and he was passing it when the lady softly called to him by his name.

“I beg your pardon, Ma’am?” said Mr. Boffin, coming to a stop.

“It is Mrs. Lammle,” said the lady.

Mr. Boffin went up to the window, and hoped Mrs. Lammle was well.

“Not very well, dear Mr. Boffin; I have fluttered myself by being—perhaps foolishly—uneasy and anxious. I have been waiting for you some time. Can I speak to you?”

Mr. Boffin proposed that Mrs. Lammle should drive on to his house, a few hundred yards further.

“I would rather not, Mr. Boffin, unless you particularly wish it. I feel the difficulty and delicacy of the matter so much that I would rather avoid speaking to you at your own home. You must think this very strange?”

Mr. Boffin said no, but meant yes.

“It is because I am so grateful for the good opinion of all my friends, and am so touched by it, that I cannot bear to run the risk of forfeiting it in any case, even in the cause of duty. I have asked my husband (my dear Alfred, Mr. Boffin) whether it is the cause of duty, and he has most emphatically said Yes. I wish I had asked him sooner. It would have spared me much distress.”

(“Can this be more dropping down upon me!” thought Mr. Boffin, quite bewildered.)

“It was Alfred who sent me to you, Mr. Boffin. Alfred said, ‘Don’t come back, Sophronia, until you have seen Mr. Boffin, and told him all. Whatever he may think of it, he ought certainly to know it.’ Would you mind coming into the carriage?”

Mr. Boffin answered, “Not at all,” and took his seat at Mrs. Lammle’s side.

“Drive slowly anywhere,” Mrs. Lammle called to her coachman, “and don’t let the carriage rattle.”

“It must be more dropping down, I think,” said Mr. Boffin to himself. “What next?”

II

The Golden Dustman Rises a Little

Mr. and Mrs. Lammle had come to breakfast with Mr. and Mrs. Boffin. They were not absolutely uninvited, but had pressed themselves with so much urgency on the golden couple, that evasion of the honour and pleasure of their company would have been difficult, if desired. They were in a charming state of mind, were Mr. and Mrs. Lammle, and almost as fond of Mr. and Mrs. Boffin as of one another.

“My dear Mrs. Boffin,” said Mrs. Lammle, “it imparts new life to me, to see my Alfred in confidential communication with Mr. Boffin. The two were formed to become intimate. So much simplicity combined with so much force of character, such natural sagacity united to such amiability and gentleness—these are the distinguishing characteristics of both.”

This being said aloud, gave Mr. Lammle an opportunity, as he came with Mr. Boffin from the window to the breakfast table, of taking up his dear and honoured wife.

“My Sophronia,” said that gentleman, “your too partial estimate of your husband’s character—”

“No! Not too partial, Alfred,” urged the lady, tenderly moved; “never say that.”

“My child, your favourable opinion, then, of your husband—you don’t object to that phrase, darling?”

“How can I, Alfred?”

“Your favourable opinion then, my Precious, does less than justice to Mr. Boffin, and more than justice to me.”

“To the first charge, Alfred, I plead guilty. But to the second, oh no, no!”

“Less than justice to Mr. Boffin, Sophronia,” said Mr. Lammle, soaring into a tone of moral grandeur, “because it represents Mr. Boffin as on my lower level; more than justice to me, Sophronia, because it represents me as on Mr. Boffin’s higher level. Mr. Boffin bears and forbears far more than I could.”

“Far more than you could for yourself, Alfred?”

“My love, that is not the question.”

“Not the question, lawyer?” said Mrs. Lammle, archly.

“No, dear Sophronia. From my lower level, I regard Mr. Boffin as too generous, as possessed of too much clemency, as being too good to persons who are unworthy of him and ungrateful to him. To those noble qualities I can lay no claim. On the contrary, they rouse my indignation when I see them in action.”

“Alfred!”

“They rouse my indignation, my dear, against the unworthy persons, and give me a combative desire to stand between Mr. Boffin and all such persons. Why? Because, in my lower nature I am more worldly and less delicate. Not being so magnanimous as Mr. Boffin, I feel his injuries more than he does himself, and feel more capable of opposing his injurers.”

It struck Mrs. Lammle that it appeared rather difficult this morning to bring Mr. and Mrs. Boffin into agreeable conversation. Here had been several lures thrown out, and neither of them had uttered a word. Here were she, Mrs. Lammle, and her husband discoursing at once affectingly and effectively, but discoursing alone. Assuming that the dear old creatures were impressed by what they heard, still one would like to be sure of it, the more so, as at least one of the dear old creatures was somewhat pointedly referred to. If the dear old creatures were too bashful or too dull to assume their required places in the discussion, why then it would seem desirable that the dear old creatures should be taken by their heads and shoulders and brought into it.

“But is not my husband saying in effect,” asked Mrs. Lammle, therefore, with an innocent air, of Mr. and Mrs. Boffin, “that he becomes unmindful of his own temporary misfortunes in his admiration of another whom he is burning to serve? And is not that making an admission that his nature is a generous one? I am wretched in argument, but surely this is so, dear Mr. and Mrs. Boffin?”

Still, neither Mr. and Mrs. Boffin said a word. He sat with his eyes on his plate, eating his muffins and ham, and she sat shyly looking at the teapot. Mrs. Lammle’s innocent appeal was merely thrown into the air, to mingle with the steam of the urn. Glancing towards Mr. and Mrs. Boffin, she very slightly raised her eyebrows, as though inquiring of her husband: “Do I notice anything wrong here?”

Mr. Lammle, who had found his chest effective on a variety of occasions, manoeuvred his capacious shirt front into the largest demonstration possible, and then smiling retorted on his wife, thus:

“Sophronia, darling, Mr. and Mrs. Boffin will remind you of the old adage, that self-praise is no recommendation.”

“Self-praise, Alfred? Do you mean because we are one and the same?”

“No, my dear child. I mean that you cannot fail to remember, if you reflect for a single moment, that what you are pleased to compliment me upon feeling in the case of Mr. Boffin, you have yourself confided to me as your own feeling in the case of Mrs. Boffin.”

(“I shall be beaten by this lawyer,” Mrs. Lammle gaily whispered to Mrs. Boffin. “I am afraid I must admit it, if he presses me, for it’s damagingly true.”)

Several white dints began to come and go about Mr. Lammle’s nose, as he observed that Mrs. Boffin merely looked up from the teapot for a moment with an embarrassed smile, which was no smile, and then looked down again.

“Do you admit the charge, Sophronia?” inquired Alfred, in a rallying tone.

“Really, I think,” said Mrs. Lammle, still gaily, “I must throw myself on the protection of the Court. Am I bound to answer that question, my Lord?” To Mr. Boffin.

“You needn’t, if you don’t like, ma’am,” was his answer. “It’s not of the least consequence.”

Both husband and wife glanced at him, very doubtfully. His manner was grave, but not coarse, and derived some dignity from a certain repressed dislike of the tone of the conversation.

Again Mrs. Lammle raised her eyebrows for instruction from her husband. He replied in a slight nod, “Try ’em again.”

“To protect myself against the suspicion of covert self-laudation, my dear Mrs. Boffin,” said the airy Mrs. Lammle therefore, “I must tell you how it was.”

“No. Pray don’t,” Mr. Boffin interposed.

Mrs. Lammle turned to him laughingly. “The Court objects?”

“Ma’am,” said Mr. Boffin, “the Court (if I am the Court) does object. The Court objects for two reasons. First, because the Court don’t think it fair. Secondly, because the dear old lady, Mrs. Court (if I am Mr.) gets distressed by it.”

A very remarkable wavering between two bearings—between her propitiatory bearing there, and her defiant bearing at Mr. Twemlow’s—was observable on the part of Mrs. Lammle as she said:

“What does the Court not consider fair?”

“Letting you go on,” replied Mr. Boffin, nodding his head soothingly, as who should say, we won’t be harder on you than we can help; we’ll make the best of it. “It’s not aboveboard and it’s not fair. When the old lady is uncomfortable, there’s sure to be good reason for it. I see she is uncomfortable, and I plainly see this is the good reason wherefore. Have you breakfasted, ma’am?”

Mrs. Lammle, settling into her defiant manner, pushed her plate away, looked at her husband, and laughed; but by no means gaily.

“Have you breakfasted, sir?” inquired Mr. Boffin.

“Thank you,” replied Alfred, showing all his teeth. “If Mrs. Boffin will oblige me, I’ll take another cup of tea.”

He spilled a little of it over the chest which ought to have been so effective, and which had done so little; but on the whole drank it with something of an air, though the coming and going dints got almost as large, the while, as if they had been made by pressure of the teaspoon. “A thousand thanks,” he then observed. “I have breakfasted.”

“Now, which,” said Mr. Boffin softly, taking out a pocketbook, “which of you two is cashier?”

“Sophronia, my dear,” remarked her husband, as he leaned back in his chair, waving his right hand towards her, while he hung his left hand by the thumb in the armhole of his waistcoat: “it shall be your department.”

“I would rather,” said Mr. Boffin, “that it was your husband’s, ma’am, because—but never mind, because, I would rather have to do with him. However, what I have to say, I will say with as little offence as possible; if I can say it without any, I shall be heartily glad. You two have done me a service, a very great service, in doing what you did (my old lady knows what it was), and I have put into this envelope a bank note for a hundred pound. I consider the service well worth a hundred pound, and I am well pleased to pay the money. Would you do me the favour to take it, and likewise to accept my thanks?”

With a haughty action, and without looking towards him, Mrs. Lammle held out her left hand, and into it Mr. Boffin put the little packet. When she had conveyed it to her bosom, Mr. Lammle had the appearance of feeling relieved, and breathing more freely, as not having been quite certain that the hundred pounds were his, until the note had been safely transferred out of Mr. Boffin’s keeping into his own Sophronia’s.

“It is not impossible,” said Mr. Boffin, addressing Alfred, “that you have had some general idea, sir, of replacing Rokesmith, in course of time?”

“It is not,” assented Alfred, with a glittering smile and a great deal of nose, “not impossible.”

“And perhaps, ma’am,” pursued Mr. Boffin, addressing Sophronia, “you have been so kind as to take up my old lady in your own mind, and to do her the honour of turning the question over whether you mightn’t one of these days have her in charge, like? Whether you mightn’t be a sort of Miss Bella Wilfer to her, and something more?”

“I should hope,” returned Mrs. Lammle, with a scornful look and in a loud voice, “that if I were anything to your wife, sir, I could hardly fail to be something more than Miss Bella Wilfer, as you call her.”

“What do you call her, ma’am?” asked Mr. Boffin.

Mrs. Lammle disdained to reply, and sat defiantly beating one foot on the ground.

“Again I think I may say, that’s not impossible. Is it, sir?” asked Mr. Boffin, turning to Alfred.

“It is not,” said Alfred, smiling assent as before, “not impossible.”

“Now,” said Mr. Boffin, gently, “it won’t do. I don’t wish to say a single word that might be afterwards remembered as unpleasant; but it won’t do.”

“Sophronia, my love,” her husband repeated in a bantering manner, “you hear? It won’t do.”

“No,” said Mr. Boffin, with his voice still dropped, “it really won’t. You positively must excuse us. If you’ll go your way, we’ll go ours, and so I hope this affair ends to the satisfaction of all parties.”

Mrs. Lammle gave him the look of a decidedly dissatisfied party demanding exemption from the category; but said nothing.

“The best thing we can make of the affair,” said Mr. Boffin, “is a matter of business, and as a matter of business it’s brought to a conclusion. You have done me a great service, a very great service, and I have paid for it. Is there any objection to the price?”

Mr. and Mrs. Lammle looked at one another across the table, but neither could say that there was. Mr. Lammle shrugged his shoulders, and Mrs. Lammle sat rigid.

“Very good,” said Mr. Boffin. “We hope (my old lady and me) that you’ll give us credit for taking the plainest and honestest shortcut that could be taken under the circumstances. We have talked it over with a deal of care (my old lady and me), and we have felt that at all to lead you on, or even at all to let you go on of your own selves, wouldn’t be the right thing. So, I have openly given you to understand that—” Mr. Boffin sought for a new turn of speech, but could find none so expressive as his former one, repeated in a confidential tone, “—that it won’t do. If I could have put the case more pleasantly I would; but I hope I haven’t put it very unpleasantly; at all events I haven’t meant to. So,” said Mr. Boffin, by way of peroration, “wishing you well in the way you go, we now conclude with the observation that perhaps you’ll go it.”

Mr. Lammle rose with an impudent laugh on his side of the table, and Mrs. Lammle rose with a disdainful frown on hers. At this moment a hasty foot was heard on the staircase, and Georgiana Podsnap broke into the room, unannounced and in tears.

“Oh, my dear Sophronia,” cried Georgiana, wringing her hands as she ran up to embrace her, “to think that you and Alfred should be ruined! Oh, my poor dear Sophronia, to think that you should have had a sale at your house after all your kindness to me! Oh, Mr. and Mrs. Boffin, pray forgive me for this intrusion, but you don’t know how fond I was of Sophronia when Pa wouldn’t let me go there any more, or what I have felt for Sophronia since I heard from Ma of her having been brought low in the world. You don’t, you can’t, you never can, think, how I have lain awake at night and cried for my good Sophronia, my first and only friend!”

Mrs. Lammle’s manner changed under the poor silly girl’s embraces, and she turned extremely pale: directing one appealing look, first to Mrs. Boffin, and then to Mr. Boffin. Both understood her instantly, with a more delicate subtlety than much better educated people, whose perception came less directly from the heart, could have brought to bear upon the case.

“I haven’t a minute,” said poor little Georgiana, “to stay. I am out shopping early with Ma, and I said I had a headache and got Ma to leave me outside in the phaeton, in Piccadilly, and ran round to Sackville Street, and heard that Sophronia was here, and then Ma came to see, oh such a dreadful old stony woman from the country in a turban in Portland Place, and I said I wouldn’t go up with Ma but would drive round and leave cards for the Boffins, which is taking a liberty with the name; but oh my goodness I am distracted, and the phaeton’s at the door, and what would Pa say if he knew it!”

“Don’t ye be timid, my dear,” said Mrs. Boffin. “You came in to see us.”

“Oh, no, I didn’t,” cried Georgiana. “It’s very impolite, I know, but I came to see my poor Sophronia, my only friend. Oh! how I felt the separation, my dear Sophronia, before I knew you were brought low in the world, and how much more I feel it now!”

There were actually tears in the bold woman’s eyes, as the soft-headed and softhearted girl twined her arms about her neck.

“But I’ve come on business,” said Georgiana, sobbing and drying her face, and then searching in a little reticule, “and if I don’t despatch it I shall have come for nothing, and oh good gracious! what would Pa say if he knew of Sackville Street, and what would Ma say if she was kept waiting on the doorsteps of that dreadful turban, and there never were such pawing horses as ours unsettling my mind every moment more and more when I want more mind than I have got, by pawing up Mr. Boffin’s street where they have no business to be. Oh! where is, where is it? Oh! I can’t find it!” All this time sobbing, and searching in the little reticule.

“What do you miss, my dear?” asked Mr. Boffin, stepping forward.

“Oh! it’s little enough,” replied Georgiana, “because Ma always treats me as if I was in the nursery (I am sure I wish I was!), but I hardly ever spend it and it has mounted up to fifteen pounds, Sophronia, and I hope three five-pound notes are better than nothing, though so little, so little! And now I have found that—oh, my goodness! there’s the other gone next! Oh no, it isn’t, here it is!”

With that, always sobbing and searching in the reticule, Georgiana produced a necklace.

“Ma says chits and jewels have no business together,” pursued Georgiana, “and that’s the reason why I have no trinkets except this, but I suppose my aunt Hawkinson was of a different opinion, because she left me this, though I used to think she might just as well have buried it, for it’s always kept in jewellers’ cotton. However, here it is, I am thankful to say, and of use at last, and you’ll sell it, dear Sophronia, and buy things with it.”

“Give it to me,” said Mr. Boffin, gently taking it. “I’ll see that it’s properly disposed of.”

“Oh! are you such a friend of Sophronia’s, Mr. Boffin?” cried Georgiana. “Oh, how good of you! Oh, my gracious! there was something else, and it’s gone out of my head! Oh no, it isn’t, I remember what it was. My grandmamma’s property, that’ll come to me when I am of age, Mr. Boffin, will be all my own, and neither Pa nor Ma nor anybody else will have any control over it, and what I wish to do it so make some of it over somehow to Sophronia and Alfred, by signing something somewhere that’ll prevail on somebody to advance them something. I want them to have something handsome to bring them up in the world again. Oh, my goodness me! Being such a friend of my dear Sophronia’s, you won’t refuse me, will you?”

“No, no,” said Mr. Boffin, “it shall be seen to.”

“Oh, thank you, thank you!” cried Georgiana. “If my maid had a little note and half a crown, I could run round to the pastrycook’s to sign something, or I could sign something in the Square if somebody would come and cough for me to let ’em in with the key, and would bring a pen and ink with ’em and a bit of blotting-paper. Oh, my gracious! I must tear myself away, or Pa and Ma will both find out! Dear, dear Sophronia, good, goodbye!”

The credulous little creature again embraced Mrs. Lammle most affectionately, and then held out her hand to Mr. Lammle.

“Goodbye, dear Mr. Lammle—I mean Alfred. You won’t think after today that I have deserted you and Sophronia because you have been brought low in the world, will you? Oh me! oh me! I have been crying my eyes out of my head, and Ma will be sure to ask me what’s the matter. Oh, take me down, somebody, please, please, please!”

Mr. Boffin took her down, and saw her driven away, with her poor little red eyes and weak chin peering over the great apron of the custard-coloured phaeton, as if she had been ordered to expiate some childish misdemeanour by going to bed in the daylight, and were peeping over the counterpane in a miserable flutter of repentance and low spirits. Returning to the breakfast-room, he found Mrs. Lammle still standing on her side of the table, and Mr. Lammle on his.

“I’ll take care,” said Mr. Boffin, showing the money and the necklace, “that these are soon given back.”

Mrs. Lammle had taken up her parasol from a side table, and stood sketching with it on the pattern of the damask cloth, as she had sketched on the pattern of Mr. Twemlow’s papered wall.

“You will not undeceive her I hope, Mr. Boffin?” she said, turning her head towards him, but not her eyes.

“No,” said Mr. Boffin.

“I mean, as to the worth and value of her friend,” Mrs. Lammle explained, in a measured voice, and with an emphasis on her last word.

“No,” he returned. “I may try to give a hint at her home that she is in want of kind and careful protection, but I shall say no more than that to her parents, and I shall say nothing to the young lady herself.”

“Mr. and Mrs. Boffin,” said Mrs. Lammle, still sketching, and seeming to bestow great pains upon it, “there are not many people, I think, who, under the circumstances, would have been so considerate and sparing as you have been to me just now. Do you care to be thanked?”

“Thanks are always worth having,” said Mrs. Boffin, in her ready good nature.

“Then thank you both.”

“Sophronia,” asked her husband, mockingly, “are you sentimental?”

“Well, well, my good sir,” Mr. Boffin interposed, “it’s a very good thing to think well of another person, and it’s a very good thing to be thought well of by another person. Mrs. Lammle will be none the worse for it, if she is.”

“Much obliged. But I asked Mrs. Lammle if she was.”

She stood sketching on the tablecloth, with her face clouded and set, and was silent.

“Because,” said Alfred, “I am disposed to be sentimental myself, on your appropriation of the jewels and the money, Mr. Boffin. As our little Georgiana said, three five-pound notes are better than nothing, and if you sell a necklace you can buy things with the produce.”

“If you sell it,” was Mr. Boffin’s comment, as he put it in his pocket.

Alfred followed it with his looks, and also greedily pursued the notes until they vanished into Mr. Boffin’s waistcoat pocket. Then he directed a look, half exasperated and half jeering, at his wife. She still stood sketching; but, as she sketched, there was a struggle within her, which found expression in the depth of the few last lines the parasol point indented into the tablecloth, and then some tears fell from her eyes.

“Why, confound the woman,” exclaimed Lammle, “she is sentimental!”

She walked to the window, flinching under his angry stare, looked out for a moment, and turned round quite coldly.

“You have had no former cause of complaint on the sentimental score, Alfred, and you will have none in future. It is not worth your noticing. We go abroad soon, with the money we have earned here?”

“You know we do; you know we must.”

“There is no fear of my taking any sentiment with me. I should soon be eased of it, if I did. But it will be all left behind. It is all left behind. Are you ready, Alfred?”

“What the deuce have I been waiting for but you, Sophronia?”

“Let us go then. I am sorry I have delayed our dignified departure.”

She passed out and he followed her. Mr. and Mrs. Boffin had the curiosity softly to raise a window and look after them as they went down the long street. They walked arm-in-arm, showily enough, but without appearing to interchange a syllable. It might have been fanciful to suppose that under their outer bearing there was something of the shamed air of two cheats who were linked together by concealed handcuffs; but, not so, to suppose that they were haggardly weary of one another, of themselves, and of all this world. In turning the street corner they might have turned out of this world, for anything Mr. and Mrs. Boffin ever saw of them to the contrary; for, they set eyes on the Lammles never more.

XVII

The Voice of Society

Behoves Mortimer Lightwood, therefore, to answer a dinner card from Mr. and Mrs. Veneering requesting the honour, and to signify that Mr. Mortimer Lightwood will be happy to have the other honour. The Veneerings have been, as usual, indefatigably dealing dinner cards to Society, and whoever desires to take a hand had best be quick about it, for it is written in the Books of the Insolvent Fates that Veneering shall make a resounding smash next week. Yes. Having found out the clue to that great mystery how people can contrive to live beyond their means, and having over-jobbed his jobberies as legislator deputed to the Universe by the pure electors of Pocket-Breaches, it shall come to pass next week that Veneering will accept the Chiltern Hundreds, that the legal gentleman in Britannia’s confidence will again accept the Pocket-Breaches Thousands, and that the Veneerings will retire to Calais, there to live on Mrs. Veneering’s diamonds (in which Mr. Veneering, as a good husband, has from time to time invested considerable sums), and to relate to Neptune and others, how that, before Veneering retired from Parliament, the House of Commons was composed of himself and the six hundred and fifty-seven dearest and oldest friends he had in the world. It shall likewise come to pass, at as nearly as possible the same period, that Society will discover that it always did despise Veneering, and distrust Veneering, and that when it went to Veneering’s to dinner it always had misgivings—though very secretly at the time, it would seem, and in a perfectly private and confidential manner.

The next week’s books of the Insolvent Fates, however, being not yet opened, there is the usual rush to the Veneerings, of the people who go to their house to dine with one another and not with them. There is Lady Tippins. There are Podsnap the Great, and Mrs. Podsnap. There is Twemlow. There are Buffer, Boots, and Brewer. There is the contractor, who is Providence to five hundred thousand men. There is the chairman, travelling three thousand miles per week. There is the brilliant genius who turned the shares into that remarkably exact sum of three hundred and seventy five thousand pounds, no shillings, and nopence.

To whom, add Mortimer Lightwood, coming in among them with a reassumption of his old languid air, founded on Eugene, and belonging to the days when he told the story of the Man from Somewhere.

That fresh fairy, Tippins, all but screams at sight of her false swain. She summons the deserter to her with her fan; but the deserter, predetermined not to come, talks Britain with Podsnap. Podsnap always talks Britain, and talks as if he were a sort of private watchman employed, in the British interests, against the rest of the world. “We know what Russia means, sir,” says Podsnap; “we know what France wants; we see what America is up to; but we know what England is. That’s enough for us.”

However, when dinner is served, and Lightwood drops into his old place over against Lady Tippins, she can be fended off no longer. “Long banished Robinson Crusoe,” says the charmer, exchanging salutations, “how did you leave the island?”

“Thank you,” says Lightwood. “It made no complaint of being in pain anywhere.”

“Say, how did you leave the savages?” asks Lady Tippins.

“They were becoming civilized when I left Juan Fernandez,” says Lightwood. “At least they were eating one another, which looked like it.”

“Tormentor!” returns the dear young creature. “You know what I mean, and you trifle with my impatience. Tell me something, immediately, about the married pair. You were at the wedding.”

“Was I, by the by?” Mortimer pretends, at great leisure, to consider. “So I was!”

“How was the bride dressed? In rowing costume?”

Mortimer looks gloomy, and declines to answer.

“I hope she steered herself, skiffed herself, paddled herself, larboarded and starboarded herself, or whatever the technical term may be, to the ceremony?” proceeds the playful Tippins.

“However she got to it, she graced it,” says Mortimer.

Lady Tippins with a skittish little scream, attracts the general attention. “Graced it! Take care of me if I faint, Veneering. He means to tell us, that a horrid female waterman is graceful!”

“Pardon me. I mean to tell you nothing, Lady Tippins,” replies Lightwood. And keeps his word by eating his dinner with a show of the utmost indifference.

“You shall not escape me in this way, you morose backwoodsman,” retorts Lady Tippins. “You shall not evade the question, to screen your friend Eugene, who has made this exhibition of himself. The knowledge shall be brought home to you that such a ridiculous affair is condemned by the voice of Society. My dear Mrs. Veneering, do let us resolve ourselves into a Committee of the whole House on the subject.”

Mrs. Veneering, always charmed by this rattling sylph, cries. “Oh yes! Do let us resolve ourselves into a Committee of the whole House! So delicious!” Veneering says, “As many as are of that opinion, say Aye—contrary, No—the Ayes have it.” But nobody takes the slightest notice of his joke.

“Now, I am Chairwoman of Committees!” cries Lady Tippins.

(“What spirits she has!” exclaims Mrs. Veneering; to whom likewise nobody attends.)

“And this,” pursues the sprightly one, “is a Committee of the whole House to what-you-may-call-it—elicit, I suppose—the voice of Society. The question before the Committee is, whether a young man of very fair family, good appearance, and some talent, makes a fool or a wise man of himself in marrying a female waterman, turned factory girl.”

“Hardly so, I think,” the stubborn Mortimer strikes in. “I take the question to be, whether such a man as you describe, Lady Tippins, does right or wrong in marrying a brave woman (I say nothing of her beauty), who has saved his life, with a wonderful energy and address; whom he knows to be virtuous, and possessed of remarkable qualities; whom he has long admired, and who is deeply attached to him.”

“But, excuse me,” says Podsnap, with his temper and his shirt-collar about equally rumpled; “was this young woman ever a female waterman?”

“Never. But she sometimes rowed in a boat with her father, I believe.”

General sensation against the young woman. Brewer shakes his head. Boots shakes his head. Buffer shakes his head.

“And now, Mr. Lightwood, was she ever,” pursues Podsnap, with his indignation rising high into those hairbrushes of his, “a factory girl?”

“Never. But she had some employment in a paper mill, I believe.”

General sensation repeated. Brewer says, “Oh dear!” Boots says, “Oh dear!” Buffer says, “Oh dear!” All, in a rumbling tone of protest.

“Then all I have to say is,” returns Podsnap, putting the thing away with his right arm, “that my gorge rises against such a marriage—that it offends and disgusts me—that it makes me sick—and that I desire to know no more about it.”

(“Now I wonder,” thinks Mortimer, amused, “whether you are the Voice of Society!”)

“Hear, hear, hear!” cries Lady Tippins. “Your opinion of this mésalliance, honourable colleagues of the honourable member who has just sat down?”

Mrs. Podsnap is of opinion that in these matters “there should be an equality of station and fortune, and that a man accustomed to Society should look out for a woman accustomed to Society and capable of bearing her part in it with—an ease and elegance of carriage—that.” Mrs. Podsnap stops there, delicately intimating that every such man should look out for a fine woman as nearly resembling herself as he may hope to discover.

(“Now I wonder,” thinks Mortimer, “whether you are the Voice!”)

Lady Tippins next canvasses the contractor, of five hundred thousand power. It appears to this potentate, that what the man in question should have done, would have been, to buy the young woman a boat and a small annuity, and set her up for herself. These things are a question of beefsteaks and porter. You buy the young woman a boat. Very good. You buy her, at the same time, a small annuity. You speak of that annuity in pounds sterling, but it is in reality so many pounds of beefsteaks and so many pints of porter. On the one hand, the young woman has the boat. On the other hand, she consumes so many pounds of beefsteaks and so many pints of porter. Those beefsteaks and that porter are the fuel to that young woman’s engine. She derives therefrom a certain amount of power to row the boat; that power will produce so much money; you add that to the small annuity; and thus you get at the young woman’s income. That (it seems to the contractor) is the way of looking at it.

The fair enslaver having fallen into one of her gentle sleeps during the last exposition, nobody likes to wake her. Fortunately, she comes awake of herself, and puts the question to the Wandering chairman. The Wanderer can only speak of the case as if it were his own. If such a young woman as the young woman described, had saved his own life, he would have been very much obliged to her, wouldn’t have married her, and would have got her a berth in an Electric Telegraph Office, where young women answer very well.

What does the genius of the three hundred and seventy-five thousand pounds, no shillings, and nopence, think? He can’t say what he thinks, without asking: Had the young woman any money?

“No,” says Lightwood, in an uncompromising voice; “no money.”

“Madness and moonshine,” is then the compressed verdict of the genius. “A man may do anything lawful, for money. But for no money!—Bosh!”

What does Boots say?

Boots says he wouldn’t have done it under twenty thousand pound.

What does Brewer say?

Brewer says what Boots says.

What does Buffer say?

Buffer says he knows a man who married a bathing-woman, and bolted.

Lady Tippins fancies she has collected the suffrages of the whole Committee (nobody dreaming of asking the Veneerings for their opinion), when, looking round the table through her eyeglass, she perceives Mr. Twemlow with his hand to his forehead.

Good gracious! My Twemlow forgotten! My dearest! My own! What is his vote?

Twemlow has the air of being ill at ease, as he takes his hand from his forehead and replies.

“I am disposed to think,” says he, “that this is a question of the feelings of a gentleman.”

“A gentleman can have no feelings who contracts such a marriage,” flushes Podsnap.

“Pardon me, sir,” says Twemlow, rather less mildly than usual, “I don’t agree with you. If this gentleman’s feelings of gratitude, of respect, of admiration, and affection, induced him (as I presume they did) to marry this lady—”

“This lady!” echoes Podsnap.

“Sir,” returns Twemlow, with his wristbands bristling a little, “you repeat the word; I repeat the word. This lady. What else would you call her, if the gentleman were present?”

This being something in the nature of a poser for Podsnap, he merely waves it away with a speechless wave.

“I say,” resumes Twemlow, “if such feelings on the part of this gentleman, induced this gentleman to marry this lady, I think he is the greater gentleman for the action, and makes her the greater lady. I beg to say, that when I use the word, gentleman, I use it in the sense in which the degree may be attained by any man. The feelings of a gentleman I hold sacred, and I confess I am not comfortable when they are made the subject of sport or general discussion.”

“I should like to know,” sneers Podsnap, “whether your noble relation would be of your opinion.”

“Mr. Podsnap,” retorts Twemlow, “permit me. He might be, or he might not be. I cannot say. But, I could not allow even him to dictate to me on a point of great delicacy, on which I feel very strongly.”

Somehow, a canopy of wet blanket seems to descend upon the company, and Lady Tippins was never known to turn so very greedy or so very cross. Mortimer Lightwood alone brightens. He has been asking himself, as to every other member of the Committee in turn, “I wonder whether you are the Voice!” But he does not ask himself the question after Twemlow has spoken, and he glances in Twemlow’s direction as if he were grateful. When the company disperse—by which time Mr. and Mrs. Veneering have had quite as much as they want of the honour, and the guests have had quite as much as they want of the other honour—Mortimer sees Twemlow home, shakes hands with him cordially at parting, and fares to the Temple, gaily.

Postscript

In Lieu of Preface

When I devised this story, I foresaw the likelihood that a class of readers and commentators would suppose that I was at great pains to conceal exactly what I was at great pains to suggest: namely, that Mr. John Harmon was not slain, and that Mr. John Rokesmith was he. Pleasing myself with the idea that the supposition might in part arise out of some ingenuity in the story, and thinking it worth while, in the interests of art, to hint to an audience that an artist (of whatever denomination) may perhaps be trusted to know what he is about in his vocation, if they will concede him a little patience, I was not alarmed by the anticipation.

To keep for a long time unsuspected, yet always working itself out, another purpose originating in that leading incident, and turning it to a pleasant and useful account at last, was at once the most interesting and the most difficult part of my design. Its difficulty was much enhanced by the mode of publication; for, it would be very unreasonable to expect that many readers, pursuing a story in portions from month to month through nineteen months, will, until they have it before them complete, perceive the relations of its finer threads to the whole pattern which is always before the eyes of the story-weaver at his loom. Yet, that I hold the advantages of the mode of publication to outweigh its disadvantages, may be easily believed of one who revived it in the Pickwick Papers after long disuse, and has pursued it ever since.

There is sometimes an odd disposition in this country to dispute as improbable in fiction, what are the commonest experiences in fact. Therefore, I note here, though it may not be at all necessary, that there are hundreds of Will Cases (as they are called), far more remarkable than that fancied in this book; and that the stores of the Prerogative Office teem with instances of testators who have made, changed, contradicted, hidden, forgotten, left cancelled, and left uncancelled, each many more wills than were ever made by the elder Mr. Harmon of Harmony Jail.

In my social experiences since Mrs. Betty Higden came upon the scene and left it, I have found Circumlocutional champions disposed to be warm with me on the subject of my view of the Poor Law. Mr. friend Mr. Bounderby could never see any difference between leaving the Coketown “hands” exactly as they were, and requiring them to be fed with turtle soup and venison out of gold spoons. Idiotic propositions of a parallel nature have been freely offered for my acceptance, and I have been called upon to admit that I would give Poor Law relief to anybody, anywhere, anyhow. Putting this nonsense aside, I have observed a suspicious tendency in the champions to divide into two parties; the one, contending that there are no deserving poor who prefer death by slow starvation and bitter weather, to the mercies of some Relieving Officers and some Union Houses; the other, admitting that there are such poor, but denying that they have any cause or reason for what they do. The records in our newspapers, the late exposure by The Lancet, and the common sense and senses of common people, furnish too abundant evidence against both defences. But, that my view of the Poor Law may not be mistaken or misrepresented, I will state it. I believe there has been in England, since the days of the Stuarts, no law so often infamously administered, no law so often openly violated, no law habitually so ill-supervised. In the majority of the shameful cases of disease and death from destitution, that shock the public and disgrace the country, the illegality is quite equal to the inhumanity—and known language could say no more of their lawlessness.

On Friday the Ninth of June in the present year, Mr. and Mrs. Boffin (in their manuscript dress of receiving Mr. and Mrs. Lammle at breakfast) were on the South Eastern Railway with me, in a terribly destructive accident. When I had done what I could to help others, I climbed back into my carriage—nearly turned over a viaduct, and caught aslant upon the turn—to extricate the worthy couple. They were much soiled, but otherwise unhurt. The same happy result attended Miss Bella Wilfer on her wedding day, and Mr. Riderhood inspecting Bradley Headstone’s red neckerchief as he lay asleep. I remember with devout thankfulness that I can never be much nearer parting company with my readers forever, than I was then, until there shall be written against my life, the two words with which I have this day closed this book:—The End.

September 2nd, 1865.